Salaam alaikum.
愿你平安
Is everything okay?
您好
Passport?
护照呢?
Could you turn off the engine?
能把发动机关下吗?
Do you speak Spanis
-Yes
-你会说西班牙语吗？-会
Could you turn off the engine?
把发动机关一下?
Your paper?
证件呢?
Your declaration? Ficha?
申报单？登记卡都在?
Papers?
证件呢?
Do you have a book? To read.
你有书看吗?
A book?
- For me.
-书？-给我
I can give you one.
我可以给你一本
But I don't know where it is.
但我不知道放哪去了
Ah, here it is.
啊，在这呢
Here it is.
找到了
Here you go.
给你
Thank you.
谢谢
Can I keep going?
我能继续开了吗?
Thank you.
谢谢
This is nothing, it's just..
这没什么 就是…
There.
好了
Thank you. Goodbye!
非常感谢再见
Fucking hell...
哦米噶
Have a safe trip!
一路平安
Good morning, ma'am.
早上好 女士
Is the mechanic here?
请问修车师傅在吗?
The mechanic ain't here
He won't take long.
师傅现在不在 不过很快就回
Come on in.
进来等吧
Thanks.
Sit.
你坐一会
Thank you.
谢谢
Sit.
坐吧
Something to eat?
要吃点什么吗?
Eat?
吃的？
Yes.
好啊
Thank you.
谢谢
（米其林客栈）
I ONLY REST IN THE STORM
Good afternoon.
I have a reservation for ONG CASA.
This is beautiful! How much is it?
哎真好看这个多少钱?
Lthinkit's too small
Lemme see
我觉得有点小了我试试看
It's too small, ain't it?
太小了吧?
It's too small.
对太小了
think find
I haven't seen it anywhere.
你觉得能找到46、47码的鞋吗？我哪都没见过有卖的
You'll find it.
有啊
Oh yeah? Where?
有吗？在哪?
-Yes.
在班迪姆这儿吗？-对
Then show me, I want to see it.
那你带我去逛逛
Marcelina, look!
哎你看玛塞丽娜
Wait, lemme see this.
别急我看看
Look at this, Marcelina.
你看这个玛塞丽娜
Good evening
- Good evening.
-晚上好-晚上好
Has anyone come lookine for
- Not yet.
-有人来找过我吗？－还没有
We've had to move your things
to room 16.
You moved my things?
Yes.
-把我的东西搬走了？－是的
We reoeived a guest
who's a longtime friend.
我们接待了一位老熟客
I apologize.
很抱歉
You're a father now, okay?
Stop it. Come on.
别闹你都当爸的人了拜托
Good evening
Good evening.
-晚上好-晚上好
Excuse me. would vou mind
turning the music down a bit?
不好意思能把音乐关点吗?
No.
不行
Quiet, people! Quiet.
安静点大伙都安静点
Nestor's son became a father today.
内斯托尔的儿子今天当爸爸了
We're celebrating
A baby was born today.
我们在庆祝呢孩子今天刚出生
We also want to rest
but we're gonna celebrate first.
Until 2 a.m. We won't stay long.
就到2点我们不会闹太久
What's going on? Good evening
晚上好有什么事吗?
Hello. Twas wondering
if you could turn the music down a bit.
你好我想问能不能把音乐声音关点?
Certainly.
当然
I'm sorry if we disturbed you, okay?
打扰到你真不好意思
Good night.
晚安
Hello.
- Yes?
-你好-什么事?
I'm Sérgio
I think they're expecting me.
Okay, he's inside.
好他在里面
I'm sorry for the heat.
抱歉这天也太热了
since we called the AC repairman.
我们等空调师傅来维修已经过一周了
Perhaps Federica can
where the project stands.
也许费德里卡能跟我们说下项目进展
Yes.
对
Yes. Good morning
Welcome, by the way.
是的早上好塞尔吉奥先欢迎你
Really, really welcome
非常非常欢迎你 真的
We've been waiting for you,
我们一直在等你
because we've had a few problems
with your predecessor, Leonardo,
因为你的前任莱昂纳多那边出了点问题
who was unable to finish
his environmental impact report,
他没能完成环境影响的评估报告
and this has hurt us a little.
我们这边就有点被动
But letme explain to you
what's changed from the old project.
我先跟你解释下这次和最初那版方案相比有什么改动
coastalarea
where the old road once passed
我们现在在一段海岸带以前的公路从这儿过
There's a river up here...
这边上游有条河
And the old plan chosen
而旧方案
by the previous government
是上届政府选定的
went through an area
它会穿过一片
that is now an environmental reserve.
已经改成生态保护区的地
We fought for it alongside
other actors, communities, etc.,
我们和其他参与方、社区之类一起争取来的
ye could recoanize this area
as an environmental reserve,
为了能把这区域划成生态自然保护区
red-specie
of hippopotamus right here.
因为这里有一种河马濒临灭绝
So we've decided to change
所以我们决定改线路
to a secondary layout,
把原线路改为次线路
south of this river.
就在这条河以南
there's a different type of area,
那边是另一种地貌
a wetland, the"bolanha."
是一片湿地叫“bolanha
Boan ice paddy
where rice grows.
“bolanha”是稻农种水稻的盐沼湿地
We also have a lot of "tabancas,"
周围还有很多“tabancas
the villages along the road,
"tabancas" 就是沿路的村子
where the road will be.
这条路会从他们附近经过
o there's a lotof work to be done
within the communities.
所以我们必须跟社区做大量沟通作
I think Glória can explain this better
我觉得格洛里娅更能说得清楚
Exactly.
没错正是这样
community
is absolutely essential
社区问题绝对关键
in any type of work or activity
任何工程、任何活动都绕不开
think that, in this case
it's really important
这次尤其重要
oialk to the communities
and make a preliminary diagnosis
所以这次必须去跟社区谈先做初步诊断
to see if this new situation can be..
弄清楚这套新方案…
accepted by everyone.
Because then there's also the issue
后面还牵扯到
of the financial backer..
资方那套说法
as a window of opportunity,
对我们来说这算是个窗口期
the change of government
that enabled us
政府换了才让我们
that first area as a reserve,
能像费德里卡说的那样把那区域定成保护区
is now a race against time
但现在我们是在跟时间赛跑
We have the money from European funds
欧盟的资金已经到位
but the Chinese won't begin construction
可中方不动工
your impact assessment report.
除非你的影响评估报告顺利通过
Okay.
好
Thank vou for allL the information
and the pressure too.
谢谢你们这些信息也谢谢这份压力
will certainly do my best
to achieve a favorable outcome.
我会尽全力做出有利结果
Better. Better than your best.
不只是尽要更进一步
Better? Yes, of course.
比尽力更进一步是是当然
I think we should also be prepared
我也觉得我们得先做好预案
in case the outcome of the report
以防报告结果
rent fromwhatLbeliev
to be your expectations.
可能跟你们期待的不一样
Absolutely.
确实
Our time is yery limited
to restart construction.
我们能施工的季节非常短
So we need the impact assessmen
as quickly as possible.
所以影响评估报告必须尽快完成
Evidently
respecting every rule and requirement,
so we can begin construction
这样才能推进施工
and avoid affecting producers.
也别影响生产
Eundamentally
to avoid throwing money away,
关键是别把钱打水漂
which isn't good.
那可一点都不好看
Hello, Aunt!
- Hello!
-姨下午好-下午好
ealthr
- How are you?
-你身体怎么样？-你呢?
- I'm fine.
-还行你呢？-我挺好的
How about you?
- I'm fine too.
-你呢？-我也挺好
I'd like to know the price of beef.
我想问问肉多少钱
This one's5.000
and with the bone, 4,000.
这块5千带骨的4千
I"Il have this one.
我要这块
This is from ocalcows
It didn't come from China.
这是自己养的不是中国来的
Howabout 3o.00o2
-No, 35.
一起3万行吗？-不行3万5
It's from local cows.
这是自己家养的
No protein nor calories
- Lower the price, I'm your customer.
没蛋白没热量-便宜点吧我是老主顾了
I have a bar. I'll make you..
我开酒吧的以后多照顾你生意
Lady, I'm selling chicken
- How much is it?
-姐这鸡要不要？-怎么卖的?
Each one costs 20,000 xof.
一只2万
This is a good chicken.
这鸡巴适得很
Tell me the real price.
你给我个实在价
20.000. Iteatsa lot
- It can't be.
-2万这鸡很能吃-不可能吧
Does ltshitgold?
-No, it shits diamonds
它拉黄金吗？-不它拉钻石
Diamonds?
钻石?
If they shit diamonds
sell me two for 22.
既然拉钻石两只卖我2万2
And those.
那边那些呢
Weioh that one
- This is good beef.
-称一下这块-这牛肉不错的
This cow only fed on grass
12 pounds.
全吃草长大的牛11斤
I'm already buying half your stall.
我都买你半个摊了
How much is that?
这得多少钱?
40,000.
4万
40,000?
4万?
It's cheap
Cheap?
-很便宜-便宜?
How much is the pepper?
-100 francs.
-辣椒多少钱？-100
No,50
I'l have 27 peppers.
不50我买27个
Okay
- Okay?
-行-可以吗?
I want to pay, here's 30,000.
我先付钱这里是3万
Lady!
夫人
HIl come back for the peppers
- You'll come for them later?
-我回头来拿辣椒-你等会再来拿?
I gotta hurry.
我赶时间
Lcomebaok ater
I"ll come back.
我等会就回来我会回来的
Get her! Get her!
拦住她拦住她
Give me my money
Pay up! Pay up!
把钱还我结账结账
Hey!
喂
Please take my bags. Take them!
请帮我拿一下包拿着
Excuse me!
不好意思
take me downtown?
- Get in.
-能送我去市中心吗？-上车吧
Good afternoon!
Could you drop me off
at Che Guevara and Frantz Fanon?
能在切·格瓦拉和弗朗茨·法农的叉路口把我放下吗?
Near the old palace. ls thatokay?
Yes.
-旧王宫那边可以不？-可以
Thanks.
谢谢
Thanks for holding onto my bags.
谢谢你帮我看行李
Don't mention it.
别客气
Is everything okay?
还好吗?
Yes, yes.
好好好
I don't know what happened.
我也不知道怎么回事
He confused me with somebody else.
他把我错认成其他人了
Over there, friend, take that opening.
那边朋友那个口子进去
No. Can't you turn? It's faster.
别这边不能转下吗？这样更快
Buddy, that way!
朋友走那边
Could you switch lanes, please?
能换个车道吗?
Buddy!
朋友
Please, could you...
拜托帮个忙
This way, friend.
走这边朋友
Hey, stop, stop! Please, stop.
哎停停停停求你了
Could you.
能不能…
Take my things!
东西帮我看着
Look at Marcelina.
你看玛塞丽娜
Thats not 14-our
it's human, look.
这不是400克的那种这是人发你看
That hair...
这头发是…
Maroelina,is it human
or just to hookup?
玛塞丽娜这头发是真的还是接的假发?
It's human!
是真发是真发
It's gotta be!
不可能不是
Marcelina!
玛塞丽娜
It's human.
是真发是真发
I believe you.
我信你
Marcelina, can you do just one braid?
玛塞丽娜你能给我编条辫子吗?
Just one, please.
就一条求你了
ike the one you did ath
the other day
就你那天在家编的那种
- What?
-嗨-什么?
Someone's here.
有人来了
- A guest.
-谁来了？-客人
Who? A guest?
谁？客人?
- Hello.
-你好-你好
ronnthe.hote
asked me to bring these bags.
酒店有人让我把这些袋子带来
They belong
Diára.
-是…-迪娅拉
Diára, that's right.
And?
然后?
Is she here?
她在吗?
She won't be back for a few days.
不她出国了过几天才回来
dunno
- Okay.
-我也不清楚-行
-Okay, thanks.
-不但我可以替她收着你放心-好谢谢
- Sérgio.
-那你叫？-塞尔吉奥
Sergio'
- Yes, and you?
-塞尔吉奥？-对你呢?
I'm Guilherme.
我叫吉列尔梅
Guilherme.
吉列尔梅
We're getting ready to go to a party.
我们正准备去个派对
we're having fun.
想来一起玩吗？挺好玩的
We're a bit crazy
- Okay.
-我们有点疯-行
You wanna come in?
你来吗?
This is Sérgio and we need.
这位是塞尔吉奥我们得…
- That's it!
-嗨塞尔吉奥-哎对就是
Girl, come say hello! All of you!
姐妹们来来打个招呼大家都来
ow's it going?
-Fine. You?
-还好吗？-还行你呢?
Hi, what's up?
你好还好吗?
Clayton.
克莱顿
Clayton? Pleasure.
克莱顿？幸会
Thanks. May I?
谢谢我能进吗?
Would you like some beer
water, juice..
你要啤酒水果汁
or my body?
还是要我?
Hello.
你好
Wait, the fox is here.
等等狐狸来了
Wait! The fox is here!
If they're around, they'll call.
他们要在附近就会打电话
Butvou have
Every outsider must have a bracelet.
可你得去外面外人都得戴手环
must be on a list at the door.
还得把这名字写在门上
Thev check the name
of everyone who goes in.
凡是进去的人他们都要查名字
Are you working for an NGO or..
你是在非政府组织还是
at a construction site?
在工地干?
Is he Brazilian?
这位帅气朋友是谁？他是巴西人吗？
He's Tuga
他是葡萄牙人
What's the difference?
- He's from Portugal.
-那有什么区别？-他从葡萄牙本土来的
What's the difference with a Brazilian?
葡萄牙人和巴西人有什么区别？
The difference
区别?
is that one is white, the other's black.
一个白一个黑
Like, I'm black, he's white.
比如我黑他白
No, you're white and he's white.
不你白他也白
What?
什么？
You're white, he's white
- Say that again!
-你白他也白-你再说一遍
I'm whit
-Yes.
-我白？-对
And him
- He's white.
－那他呢？-他也白
You're crazy, and he's crazy!
你疯他也疯了
That's the only explanation.
只能这么解释
He's white, I'm black.
他白我黑
He's Portuguese, I'm Brazilian.
He colonized, I was colonized.
他是殖民的我是被殖民的
When you put it like that, I get it.
你这么一说我就懂了
I'm the one who's black.
我是那个黑的
I'd argue you're a beautiful black man.
要我说你黑得很漂亮真的
You're white.he's white
What's the difference?
你白他也白有什么区别?
I'm not white, baby
I'm not speaking to you.
我不白宝贝我不跟你说了
I'm not white.
No, I'm not white.
不我不白
You're white.
你白
I'm not white.
我不白
I'm-black
- No, we're the black ones.
-我是黑的-不我们才是黑的
Sérgio! Good to see you!
嗨塞尔吉奥见到你真好
Damn, Marcelina!
靠玛塞丽娜
I'm gonna get a friend of mine.
我得去接个朋友
I don't know if we're getting in.
不知道今天能不能进
We will. We'll get in.
能走走进去吧
Who are they?
哎他们是谁?
My-colleagues
- Ditch them. Just you.
-是我同事-把他们留这你一个来
Just you
- Can't they get in too?
－就你-他们也不能进吗?
We"ll try.
我们试试
How did you end up here?
你怎么跑到这边来了?
I traveled here
我游历到这此
looking for something I haven't found
and I don't know if I ever will..
我在路上找一样东西还没找到我也不知道能不能找到
But I've come across...
但我发现一件事
this idea that I didn't come
from where I thought I did.
就是我来的地方跟我以为的不一样
Because when I left Brazil,
因为我离开巴西时
I always thought
I'd assert my African roots.
一直以为在这里能确认我非洲的根
Do you feel at home here?
你在这有家的感觉吗?
Most of the time, I feel lost,
我大多数时候都觉得迷茫
Idunno. After all
we never seem to be where we are.
可…我也说不清说到底我们好像从来不在自己所在的地方
You think so?
-I believe so.
-你也这么想？-我是这么想
Aren't you here now?
你现在不就在这儿吗?
I am in a lot of different places
one of them just happens to be here.
我在很多地方这里只是其中一个
Okay
-What about you?
-好－那你呢?
What's your power?
你的本事是什么？
I'm gonna sound pretentiou
- Like I was..
-听起来可能很装－像我以前那样
I'm gonna say: "I'm here now."
我会说我就在这儿
Is that too...
会不会太…
Perhaps it's too..
也许太…
I don't know how to use the word.
我也不知道该用什么词
Say the first that comes into your mind.
想到什么就说什么
Perhaps it's too naive
to say this is the place.
也许说这里就是归宿太天真
It would be too...
那也太
beautiful, actually.
美好了说真的
Yeah?
是吗?
Of course!'Cause being here
would mean to actually be here.
当然因为在这就意味着真的在这
I dunno, there's a lotta people here.
不知道这儿人太多了
But how do you see me?
A white man who came from Europe.
嗯…一个从欧洲来的白人
A white man, son of a European..
一个白欧洲的孩子
Clear-eyed...
眼神很清亮
Who's here.
他在这儿
Who's here..
在这儿…
And that somehow scares me.
不知怎么就让我害怕
both sides of the current.
像站在水流两边
It scares me..
我会害怕
against the flow, with the flow
underneath the flow.
逆着流顺着流流下面还有流
I don't know why.
我也不知道为什么
Maybe that's what I'm looking for.
也许这就是我在找的
Against the flow?
- Always!
-逆流？-一直都是
But what's with all these questions?
可你怎么老问这些?
What is it you really wanna know?
-I dunno.
你到底想知道什么？-我也不知道
I'd like to know more.
我想…多了解一点
I'd like to know more about you too.
我也想多了解你
Tell me about yourself.
What have you found in Guinea
you haven't found in Europe?
A lotta things.
很多
I'm just gonna complain
about my lipstick.
我只是想吐槽一下我的口红
I'm sorry
抱歉
Why did you wipe your mouth?
你刚才为什么擦嘴?
I dunno.
Because of the lipstick, I guess.
不知道可能是口红吧
I didn't like it, actually.
其实我不太喜欢
The regretful urge.
那种后悔的冲动
The hand on the mouth after one kiss.
亲完就用手捂嘴那一下
1dunno
People say it's white people stuff.
不知道听过很多人说这就是白人的毛病
White people stuff?
白人的毛病?
I really hope you're not one of those
我真希望你不是那种人
who take one look at a person's skin
只看一眼别人的肤色
and think they know
everything about them
就觉得自己什么都懂
I don't look
I feel it in my skin, not in my eyes.
我不是那样看人的我是用皮肤去感受不是用眼睛
That's different.
But you're not gonna get that.
Am I hurting you in any way?
我有伤到你吗?
Your blood is.
And at some point you have
and still do.
你曾经伤过我现在也样
-Me?
- Yeah.
-我？-对
It's always the same.
你们一直都这样
You come to us
all tender and affectionate,
你们来找我们总是温柔又亲热
wanting to heal wounds
you yourselves have caused.
想治好你们亲手造成的伤口
I've actually met a white person
who healed my wounds.
Really?
- Unfortunately. Ain't that funny?
The motherfuckers
still wanna heal our wounds.
这些狗娘养的还真想治我们的伤
You're very predictable.
你太好猜了
I can literally read your face.
我甚至能看穿你的心思
It's yourrae
- You're probably right.
-这是你们这个种族的问题-你可能说对了
You're probably right.
你可能说对了
Motherfucker.
狗娘养的
How did it go?
我怎么做的?
I'm trying to remember.
我在想
My sister-in-law told Barbosa
我嫂子去跟巴尔博萨讲
That I've taken a lover
说我心里另有其人
I'Il stil have my own water to drink
我的水我自己喝
My sister-in-law told Barbosa
我嫂子去跟巴尔博萨讲
Evenif ml
I won't lose a thing
婚姻散了我不亏
Oh, okay.
哦好
My sister-in-law...
我嫂子…
I know I won't lose a thing
婚姻散了我不亏
My sister-in-law told Barbosa
我嫂子去跟巴尔博萨讲
that how the song goes?
Yes.
-歌词是这样吗？-对
Barbosa<
That since I've taken a lover
我嫂子去跟巴尔博萨讲说我心另有其
enif arriage ends
I'Il stil have my own water to drink
婚姻散了我的水我自己喝
in 1444
他们说1444年就来到我们国家
an effective occupation in 1912.
可直到1912年才算真正实现有效占领
After the Berlin Conference.
你能想象吗？柏林会议之后
Don't forget that between 1912 and 1935,
别忘了1912到1935年之间
there was a "pacification" war.
有一场所谓的平定战争
That meant divide to better conquer.
就是分而治之
ister
- You like these liberation stories
-听着-你就爱听这些解放故事
The old fighter telling the story.
老战士讲故事那套
No, he's right
That's how the fight began.
不他没说错战斗就是这么开始的
W/ith the disruption of our groups
Yes! Resistance has always existed.
-从我们队伍被打散开始-对抵抗一直都在
Since colonialism started
resistance has existed.
殖民一开始抵抗就没停过
The liberation struccl
That's what came after.
解放战争之后就是这些
With all its mistakes
也带着一堆错误
about the liberation struggle.
妈妈最懂这场解放战争
She can tell you what happened.
她能告诉你发生了什么
That's what came after.
之后就是这样
Mama, don't drop the gun!
妈别把枪扔了啊
Our parents suffered the most.
我们父母遭的罪最多
Forced labor,
强迫劳动啊
clearing roads, paying taxes.
修路啊缴税啊
The "hut tax"?
棚屋税?
Whatwasitcalled?
The census.
他们还会…那叫什么…来普查
Census?
Census.
-普查？-普查
The station chiefs
驻地长官
would warn the village chiet
the chieftain,
会通知村长、酋长
that on this day
there would be a census.
说哪天要普查
From the age of 18.
从18岁开始
Each family would gather
at a clearing in the village.
每家都得去村里的空地集合
Each would take their place
各自站好
to count the-number of people
in the family
数清家里有多少口人
They'dcome and ask
how old they were,
他们会来问年纪
because children didn't have to pay.
因为孩子不用交
Iremember this man
from the Manjak tribe,
我记得一个曼雅克族的人
they asked him:"Your age?"
And he said: "15 years old."
他们问他多他说15岁
they asked another one
"15 years old."
又问一个15岁
"You're the father ow old are
"15 years old."
再问那个农夫你多大他也说15岁
They aske
The father and the children?"
他们问父亲和孩子你们都15岁?
They used to say "fiveteen."
他们不会说就会说15岁
"Fiveteen" years old.
15岁
came to the African coast.
欧洲人来到非洲海岸后
conflict started.
冲突就开始了
Confliot over the land
over the enforcement of religion,
为土地争为宗教争
to take over there.
还会掳走女孩把人带走
This brought on tribal wars.
这引发了部落战争
They created strateqies
alliances with kings, chieftains.
他们搞策略跟国王、酋长结盟
They created a form of marriage.
还搞出一种婚姻形式
comeand say they wantec
to marry the chieftain's daughter
他们会来说想娶酋长的
They would baptize the chieftain.
他们会给酋长施洗
Like today, right? Baptism?
就像现在那样是吧施洗?
It started back then.
那时候就开始了
Youwoul aptizeg
to become God-fearing,
你得受洗才算敬畏上帝
to be afraid of hurting your neighbor
不敢伤害邻居
as you respected your father and mother,
还要孝敬父母
you should also respect authority.
也要服从权威
cause thevre our a atparents
nationwide
因为他们是我们全国的大家长
How are you, friend?
你好吗朋友?
Welcome!
欢迎
nk
- Are you well?
-谢谢-还好吗?
This is Sérgio, our new associate.
- Pleasure. Welcome home!
-你好-幸会欢迎回家
He drove all the way from Portugal.
他从葡萄牙一路开过来的
My God, you must be dead.
天啊你肯定累坏了
Almost
-Right.
-差不多-就是
isten Horácio is over
with his wife and baby.
听着奥拉西奥在那边带着婆和孩子
He's been kidnapped by photographers
He'll join you soon.
被摄影师拽住了会就来
- How was your trip?
-好极了谢谢-旅途怎么样?
- It was great.
-很棒吗？-挺好的
The country, the heat?
这国家这热气?
It feels good, doesn't it?
感觉不错吧?
Honey! I need to talk to you.
亲爱的我得跟你聊几句
Congratulations!
-Thank you very much.
Come take a picture with us, girl!
姑娘来跟我们拍张照
Can I?
我可以吗?
Don't tell me you're a saint
now that you're married.
别告诉我你结婚了就变乖了
Watch it, girl.
注意点姑娘
Now can I take one with Horácio?
那我现在能跟奥拉西奥拍张吗?
You want me to hold the baby?
Sure.
-要我抱着宝宝吗？-行
Girl
- Wonderful.
-姑娘-真棒
Let me just go wet my whistle.
我先去润润嗓子
Go on then
- You two... Okay.
-去吧-你们两个-好
Comrade!
同志
- Thank you for inviting me.
-你好吗？-谢谢你邀请我
Sérgio!
塞尔吉奥
Pleasure! Welcome, welcome!
幸会欢迎欢迎
There's no better way tointroduce him
than at a party at your house.
在你家办派对介绍他再好不过了
Oh, come on..
哦别这样
Have you had anything to drink, to eat?
We have everything.
你有吃好喝好吗？我们这什么都有
First, ld like-to offer this
to the parents, of course.
首先当然得把这个献给长辈
hope it's still good
It made quite a journey.
希望还没坏走了很远的路
This is wonderful
From the Alentejo, my favorite.
太好了阿连特茹来的我的最爱(葡萄牙中南部的一个区)
What do you call it?
你们怎么形容?
-This one is.
-很顺口是吧？-这瓶可以
Nodou
If it wasn't so hot.
当然要是不这么热就好了
Now a gin, right?
现在来杯杜松子酒吧?
Shall we?
来吗?
Yes, good idea.
好主意
Let's do it.
走走
Excuse me.
不好意思
I heard you drove all the way here.
我听说你一路开车过来的
I've always wanted to make that trip
but with my work..
我也一直想这么走一趟但工作不允许
oave?
- A normal gin.
-你们这有哪种杜松子酒？-普通的
Normal? No, come on.
With red berries.
-Go ahead.
-好的稍等-去吧
that we're still looking at the dossiers.
我想跟您说我们还在看那些档案
will only start on Monday or so.
大概周一才会正式开始
Sorry, I'm a workaholic.
抱歉我是工作狂
Lkeep
to be as available as I am to work.
总以为别人也会像我一样随时能开工
But you knol
what people are like over here.
但你也知道这边的就那样
They don't have the same objectivity
as they do up there.
节奏跟上面不一样
People here still hold on to the past,
这里的人总被过去绑着
the meaning of things
the trees, the rivers..
事物的意义树木河流…
That may be
I know you know that,
不是说它们没意义你懂的
but it's a matter of allegiance,
of focus
可这只是忠诚的问题也是注意力的问题
To innovate, evolve, experiment.
要创新要进化要实验
Having the ability to want more
to want the best, the new.
想要更多想要更好想要更新这是一种能
They want that here
that's what everyone says.
这里有这种冲动都说想要
They don't want to say no.
It's amazing
他们不会跟你说不尤其是这点这太不可思议了
No one says no.
没人跟你说不
But they are loyal to what they know,
可他们只忠于自己熟悉的东西
loyal to what they respect
loyal to what makes them feel safe.
忠于他们尊重的忠于能让他们安心的
To innovate and evolve
that's a tough negotiation.
要创新要进步这事很难谈
I'm not sure you get it.
That's why you're here.
我不确定你懂不懂你来这儿就是因为这个
That's why we must solve this
before the rainy season begins.
所以雨季来之前我们必须把这事解决
We will follow every rule.
我们会按规矩来
As long as we follow the rules
we should be fine.
只要守规矩一切都没问题
I'm telling you all this
我跟你说这些
because you just got here.
m counting on you
Yes.
- 我指望你了-嗯
a.untis
They're returning to the countryside.
我姨今天走要回乡下了
She wants to say goodbye.
Come on
- Okay.
-走吧-好
We'll finish this later, enjoy your gin.
话先说到这好好喝你的杜松子酒
See you.
回头见
At the beginning of the fight.
if anything happened in the tabanca,
战斗刚开始时村里要是出了事
people had a way of communioating
with the comrades.
大家有办法跟同志互通消息
For example
the Balantas have the "bumbulum."
比如巴兰塔人有种鼓叫“bumbulum
When they-played
those who know Balanta would understand
他们一敲懂巴兰塔的人就能听明白
They would know
someone died in the tabanca.
他们会知道村里有人死了
It was a way of communicating
这是一种传话方式
with other villages
that there was danger.
告诉别的村子这儿有危险
They'd also knov
if the Tugas were coming.
他们也会知道葡萄牙人要来了
Just like that bird. the tchui tchui
- Yes, the tchui tchui
-就像那种鸟叫“tchuitchui” -对 “tchui tchui"
For example, at night, in the country
if you heard the tchui tchui
比如晚上在乡下你要是听到tchuitchui叫
you knew something was going on
Either an animal or the Tugas
就知道出事了可能是野兽也可能是葡萄牙人
So the village would be ready
and fighters would take precautions.
村子就会戒备战士也会做好准备
When the armed conflict began,
武装冲突一开始
people left town to mobilize.
大家就离开城里去动员
Our people were nformed
that a war was taking place
我们的人被告知战争打响了
and we wol
against the Portuguese
我们要对抗葡萄牙人
to ensure our freedom
为了争取自由
and become citizens of our land
也为了做这片土地的公民
When the
you'd have to be ready.
收税的头儿一来你就得准备好
therwise
the soldiers would come with their whips
不然士兵就会拿着鞭子过来
To kick your ass.
狠狠抽你的屁股
I remember they wore khaki shorts.
我记得他们穿卡其短裤
They ran through the village.
在村里到处跑
fLthev caught someone
they'd hit them.
逮到谁就打谁
They hit a lot
And no one asked why.
打得很凶也没人敢问为什么
That's something that mobilized mar
to join the fight
就是这些事逼得人去参战
What's up?
怎么了?
Do you understand Creole?
你想喝杯吗？你懂克奥尔语吗?
No. Very little.
Come oninl
Come have a drink, come here.
进来吧来喝一杯来这边
for the heat in Bissau, trust me.
冰啤是比绍解暑最好用的信我
If you want cashew wine...
还要腰果酒吗?
Don't kill the man with cashew.
her
and you're giving him cashew!
他才刚到比绍你就想用腰果酒把他灌倒
Cashew wine is really strong!
腰果酒可烈了
To us!
来干一杯
Make yourself at home.
当自己家别拘着
How are you?
- I'm okay
-你怎么样？-我还行
ything all right?
Yeah.
Hello!
- Hello!
-你好-你好
Sérgio
Yes?
-听着 塞尔吉奥-嗯?
Come on, join us outside.
走出来一下
We have croquettes, rissoles,
我们有炸丸子还有肉饼
hinos from here
local fruit.
还有些本地水果
I'mcoming
我就来
Come!
过来
Hey.
喂
You're everywhere.
你到处都在
Your name is..?
你叫?
Sérgio.
塞尔吉奥
Are you enjoying the party?
派对好玩吗?
I am.
挺好
Just tell me one thing.
我就问一句
How has someone who's just arrived
一个刚到的人
ended up here?
怎么会在这儿?
How do you know I've just arrived?
你怎么知道我刚到?
You smell like the airport, sweetheart.
你身上全是机场味我一闻就知道
actuall
but I've only just arrived.
我其实是开车来的但确实是刚到
-To us.
-干杯-干杯
refuse to grow old
So my knees won't lose their strength
我拒绝变老我的膝盖不能软
I still have a long path to take
我的路还长
refuse to grow old
So my hands won't turn soft
我拒绝变老我的双手不能软
I need them to build our country
还得用它们建设国家
Irefuse to grow old
A meaningless old age
我拒绝变老那种空洞的老去
They can bury my body
It doesn't bother me
它在折腾我的身体我不在乎
refuse to grow old
For the love I feel for you, Guinea-Bissau
我拒绝变因为我爱你内亚比绍
refuse to grow old
For the love I feel for you
我拒绝变老因为我爱你
refuse to grow old
For the love I feel for you, Cape Verde
I refuse to grow old
For the love
我拒绝变老为了爱
I refuse to grow old
我拒绝变老
- How are you doing?
-身体怎么样？-你怎么样?
- We're good.
-我们挺好的你们呢？-都挺好的
- Hi, Sérgio! How are you?
-嗨费代里卡-塞尔吉奥你怎么样?
You finally made it to the site.
你总算到工地了
Good morning
早上好
Can you tell where you are?
你搞清楚自己在哪了吗?
No, not really.
没有不太清楚
Dverthere those wood
by those tall trees,
那边最远处那林子树很多的地方
you'll see the area
往北再走50公里左右
as a natural reserve.
就是我们划出来的自然保护区
Now, this Il include
the new plan.
现在这里会纳入新方案
the new road would be built
新路会修在这
the new layout,
新的布局
folloy miles
all the way to the desert.
会路沿着岛直延伸到那边好公直到沙漠
Here, farmers usually build
这一般是这样种植户会在水渠边
a levee along the canal,
修一圈堤坝
uts across mang
and keeps the salt water out for years
然后砍红树林几年内不让咸水进来
until the whole land is cleared.
等把整片地的盐分洗掉
are the Balanta people.
红树林稻作最在行的是巴兰塔
There are other ethnleities
the Papels, the Manjak, even the Floups,
后来还有别的族群佩佩尔曼迪亚还有菲卢佩
who have adopted the same technique.
也用上了同样的办法
And the road will be near, right?
公路会从这附近过是吗?
The road will cross the bolanha.
对公路会从这稻中间穿过去
a much larger layout, right?
那线路就得绕得更大吧?
Yes, the layout will be much larger.
对线路会大很多当然
It'll probably cross the river.
可能还会跨过那条河
We must also consider its social impact
我们也得考虑社会影响
people don't lose their land.
Yes, but even if we spend more,
是但就算成本更高也值得
we shouldmaintair orotectec
a reserve for the hippos,
因为能保住一区域做成保护区给河马留个栖息地
especiallv beca here are
30 animals left of this species.
特别是河马这是仅存的一种大概只剩30只了
The other species, in the islands,
别的种群在岛上
are different, so obviousl
this area has to be protected.
已经算是不同的品种了这地方显然应该保护
This is a very difficult work, Sérgio,
塞尔吉奥 这活很苦
which unfortunately
cannot be mechanized.
可惜没法用机器
可惜没法用机器干
still in use today.
这是个祖辈传下来的法子现在还在用
ould you ask if l can go
take some pictures and talk to them?
你问问我能不能过去拍张照跟他们聊聊?
Of course you can.
可以当然可以
Good morning!
早上好
May I take a picture?
我可以拍照吗?
- Yes.
可以吗？-可以
May I?
我可以吗?
Bojan,
what they're doing now.
布贾那麻烦问问他们现在在做什么？
Why are they doing this?
他们为什么要这样做?
He wants to know what you're doing.
他想知道你们在做什么
and we can't grow rice.
要是咸水渗过来我们就种不了稻
goes through to the other side,
因为咸要是去到另一边
their rice won't grow.
他们就种不出稻子
The rice stays on this side.
稻田只能留在这边
tothe other side now
Yes.
-那他们现在要去那边了？-对
Why?
为什么?
Because the water's here already.
因为这边的水已经来了
We can't keep dredging the mud.
我们没法一直清淤
What happened?
怎么了?
I think I cut myself.
我好像割到自己了
What is this?
这是什么?
That was an oyster.
是牡蛎
An oyster
Careful, careful.
牡蛎-小心小心
They're only good to eat.
这东西就只适合吃
No?
-没人－那边没人吗?
Is no one here?
- No.
-人还没到吗？-没有
The dispatcher hasn't arrived yet?
-No.
-调度员还没到？-没到
Lady, there are a lotof people
waiting in there.
士有一大群人等在那
We've been waiting for the dispata
since this morning
我们从早上等调度员等到现在
I think it'll be sorted out today.
我以为今天能办好
We've been here since this morning.
我们一大早就来了
In here?
在里面?
Hey.boss
Good afternoon.
-你好老板-下午好
I brought money for the
It's been sitting here for 4 months.
我把钱带来了这车在这放了4个月了
Can we go now?
-Yes.
-我们现在能走吗？-可以
be right back.
- Okay.
-就在那边-好
- Hello!
下午好各位-你好
How are you?
你好吗?
good, give me your blessll
- I'm good.
-挺好请赐福-我很好
Uncle Nico.
尼科叔叔
Dona Domingas!
多娜·多明加斯
All good in the neighborhood?
邻里都好吧?
Yeah, I'm just here
- You're here?
-好我就是来这-你在这?
/'s-DonaDominqas?
- I'm here.
-外公多娜·多明加斯还好吗？-我在这
- You're okay?
-我挺好-你没事吧?
vou sure2
- I'm okay.
-你确定？-我没事
Really okay?
-Yes.
-真没事？-真没事
You'll be even better now.
你马上就会更好的
Grandpa
- Diára, long time no see!
You can say that again!
- How long has it been?
-真是好久啊-过多久了?
How are you?
- I'm good! And you?
-你怎么样？-我挺好你呢?
I'm good
- You're good?
-我也好-挺好的吧?
- He's lost in the world.
-有我兄弟的消息吗？-他在这世上迷路了
Diogo will be in charge of the car.
妈车就交给迪奥戈负责
he'll bring you 65 thousand.
每周五他带6万5过来
If there's more, it's for him.
不多不少多出来算他的
- Beti, stop!
-你怎么这么瘦了？-贝蒂别别
Why are you so thin?
- Beti, stop!
-你怎么这么瘦了？-贝蒂别别
-I'll put a plate on the table
- I don't wanna eat.
-我把盘子摆上-我不想吃
I wanna stay sexy.
我想显得性感点
Look, I brought you some lemon.
看我给你带了柠檬
Mama!
妈妈
One more thing.…
还有件事
lready told Dioqo
if there's any trouble with the car,
我跟迪奥戈说过车要是出问题
he should call me, not the mechanic.
让他打给我别找修车师傅
Okay?
- Okay.
-行吗？-行
Look what I've found!
看看我发现谁了
Have you come say hello to your aunt?
你是来跟你姨妈打招呼的吗?
They say they're very glad...
她说他们很高兴
The roads are terrible,
but the trip went well,
路很烂 但一路还算顺利
thank God.
谢天谢地
你就住在这附近吗?
我来这儿是想看看
一个小东西 水泵
他们想带你看看厕所
This is the first latrine.
这是第一个厕所
Each family has their own latrine,
we're gonna see them all later.
他们每家都有一个 之后我们还会去看别的家庭
看起来真不错也很干净
灰桶在哪儿?
Where did you put the bucket of...
你放哪了那个桶…
Ashes?
- Yes, ashes.
－灰桶？-对灰桶
Hortência said the bucket
was in the bathroom.
奥滕西娅说灰桶本来在厕所里
But the children smilled it
and she took it away.
可孩子打翻了她就拿走了
那你能说说以前没有这个厕所的时候你们怎么办吗?
What did you do
before you had the latrine?
你们没厕所之前怎么办？
别不好意思 我们都这样
You can say it, we all do it.
你说吧 我们都干过
Ask her if she's happy
to have a latrine.
问问她 现在对新厕所满意吗?
Ask her how she feels now.
问问她现在什么感受
Hortência,
they're asking how you feel.
奥滕西娅他们问你感觉怎么样
Are you happy to have this latrine?
你有了这个厕所开心吗?
I'm very happy.
我很开心
Because when rains,
if I'm in the woods, I get wet.
因为下雨时 我去林子里会淋湿
I'm very happy.
我很开心
She's very happy with her new latrine
because when it rains
she doesn't have to go to the woods.
她很开心现在有了新的厕所
因为雨季她不用再往林子里跑了
看到它用起来了真好 我们也希望今后
你们能一直用下去 我们在这的工作就能结束
你们也能把它延续下去 你们有钱去做
只是得把钱找出来 没有我们也能做
我想说我们最终的目标是
我们能退出让你们能独立把孩子照顾好
同时也希望你们自己主动起来我们在这儿只是帮你们把路铺平
Our goal here in Guinea-Bissau
我们在几内亚比绍的目标
is that you take care of this initiative
是让你把这个项目管起来
and look after your families...
也把家里照看好
What's your name again? Sérgio?
My name? Sérgio.
你叫什么来着塞尔吉奥？-我的名字？塞尔吉奥
I wanted to ask you something
If it's true what they say.
我想跟你确认一个事，看看他们说的是不是真的
Thev say in Lisbon,
you put drinking water in the toilet.
他们说你们那边会把饮用倒进厕所
- Drinking what?
- Water. Do you put it in the toilet?
－喝的水？-水你们倒进厕所?
- Me?
- You people, there in Lisbon.
-我们？-你们的人 里斯本那边
-Yes.
- You do that?
- 是这样 - 你们真这么干?
You do that?
你们真这么干?
Is that true?
千真万确?
No, you misunderstood me.
不 你误会我了
- It's true - It's true?
- 是真的 - 这是真的？
You take drinking water
and put it in the toilet?
你们把饮用水倒进厕所?
- In the toilet.
- In the toilet?
－倒进厕所-倒在厕所里?
Is that how you do it?
你们就是这么用的?
I don't believe you.
我才不信
- Is it?
-没骗你-是真的?
Isit?
- Me and all...
- White people.
-我也是 还有大家..．-白人嘛
Is that how you do it?
你们就这么用?
As a token gratitude,
the Budjin community
为表谢意 布金社区
would like to give something
to the delegation.
给代表团备了礼物
We are also organizing
a lunch for the delegation.
同时我们也为代表团安排了午餐
The head of the women from the village
村里的妇女负责人来自塔班加
will offer you the cloth.
会把这块布送给你们
We have other tabancas to visit.
我们还要去别的村子不能再等了
我们现在得走 非常抱歉 非常感谢你们的款待
- Bye!
- Bye! Thank you!
-再见-再见 谢谢你们
Stop saying my name!
别再叫我名字了
From now on my name is Juniper.
从现在起我叫杜松子
Marcelina, get up and help me.
玛塞丽娜起来帮我
Enjoy!
玩得开心
You choose.
你来选
You're a woman.
你是女人
It depends.
那得看情况
Be careful.
小心点
You're a woman, Guilherme.
你是女人 吉列尔梅
Come here and we'll see which one of us
is more woman.
过来让你看看谁更像女人
Guilherminha!
吉列尔米尼娅
I can also be Guilherminha.
也可以叫吉列尔米尼娅
If you take good care of me, I can.
你要是把我伺候好 就行
You're gonna get hammered...
你会喝趴下
You're gonna get hammered.
Be careful...
小心点
Who ordered beer?
谁点的啤酒?
How are you?
你好吗?
Who ordered it?
- I"l have kaimosa
-谁点的？-我要西柚香槟鸡尾酒
Do we have kaimosa?
我们有西柚香槟鸡尾酒吗?
Did you see who just got here?
-Who?
Your new friend.
你新朋友
He seems to be getting along
with Marcelina, Edmilson.
看起来他连玛塞丽娜还有埃德米尔松都混熟了
Look at him trying to fit in
pretending everything's all right.
看他拼命想混进来的样子还有点好笑
It's kinda funny, actually.
说真的有点好笑
But his hair is hydrated
the little starched shirt..
头发梳得板正衬衫还熨得硬挺
Someone must be ironing his clothes
the classic pants.
看来有人给他熨衣服还有那条经典小西裤
What NGO does he work for?
他给哪个非政府组织干活?
I think it's a humanitarian NGO
我觉得是人道非政府组织
AlLNcOs are humanitarian
aren't they?
他们不都说自己是人道的嘛朋友?
tLthen
- Or pretend to be humanitarian.
-那就是这个-或者装作人道
Then that's it, girl.
You-like this tarian-thing
-Me?
-你就爱这套人道主义-我?
Girl, you're human!
姐们你也是人
- I'Il sit over here.
－不-我坐这边
Have you been eating?
哎你们刚在吃东西?
Do you see this blinking red light?
看到那盏红灯在闪吗?
rea
but it's blinking in here, the radar.
其实是想象的可它在这儿闪我的雷达
- The closer he gets, the more it blinks.
-真在闪吗？-他越靠近越闪
Really?
真的?
You believe that?
你真信这个?
Self-confidence is everything!
自信就是一切
Guilherme...
吉列尔梅…
Let's see if your radar is off.
Careful!
-我看看你的雷达准不准-小心哦
You can find your own radar
instead of searching for mine.
你找你的雷达去别盯着我的
- A proposal?
－我有个提议-提议?
Since you seem to trust that radar.
既然你这么信这雷达
Wanna hear it?
Yes, a lot
- No!
-想-不
Step back
so I can look you in the eye.
别乱动我想好好看着你
Since you seem to trust that radar,
既然你这么信你的雷达
I think we should see
我觉得该比比
who gets there first.
看谁先到
Who gets there first?
看谁先到?
Let's bet on it.
赌一把
Whoever eats first..
谁先吃到就赢
target
- The food..
-目标-是吃的
And takes a bi
- Wins.
-谁先吃到-谁赢
III win.
我会赢
IIl win.
Girl!
- Girl!
-姐们-姐们
Look me in the eye!
看着我的眼睛
Girl!
姐妹
Girl, I love you.
姐妹我爱你
love vou too
- You know I love you.
-我也爱你-你知道我爱你
But you know I hate losing,
可你也知道我讨厌输
and I'm telling you right now
that I'm gonna win.
我现在就告诉你我会赢
No hard feelings!
别往心里去
Guilherme.
吉列尔梅
Unbreakable vow.
终身发誓
Easy! No!
哎轻点别
Unbreakable vow
-I'm out!
-终身发誓-我不玩了
What's up?
怎么了?
The Papels suck
- What do you mean?
-这帮白人真烂-你什么意思?
They stole my dog to have a ceremony.
他们偷了我的狗去办仪式
My mother is Papel.
我妈是帕佩尔人
The Papels suck.
帕佩尔人真烂
And who is this new friend?
你们这新朋友是谁?
This is Boss.
Gui! Get the towels!
吉拿毛巾
Marcelina!
玛塞丽娜
Here!
给
Diára!
迪娅拉
Here! Don't let these chairs get wet!
给这些不能沾水
Unbelievable!
太离谱了
Gui, leave it!
吉别管了
Everything's wet. Just leave it.
全湿透了走吧
Let's just send people on their way.
让大家都散了吧
Did you pay the whole bill?
你把账全结了?
Yes, everyone did.
结了全都结了
Sérgio is tired.
塞尔吉奥累了
Me?
我?
- No.
-对-没有
didnlt see you.
- No, no.
-我没看见你-不不
Wyhen the
I didn't see you.
雨刚下那会儿我真没看见你
at this time of year?
一年中的这个时候都会下雨吗?
Does it usually rain
at this time of year?
一年中的这个时候都会下雨吗?
Marcelina, please.
玛塞丽娜拜托
Thanks, Sérgio.
谢谢你塞尔吉奥
Let's go home.
我们回家吧
Go ahead.
啊你先走
No, I'll wait for you.
不我等你
Thanks, girls.
谢谢姐妹们
Thank wol
-You're welcome!
-不客气-不客气
See you tomorrow.
明天见
Will you close the bar for us?
你能帮我们把店关了吗?
Sérgio
-Yes?
-塞尔吉奥-怎么了?
My hands are wet
would you mind turning off that light?
我手是湿的你能帮我关下那盏灯吗?
The light switch's right there.
开关在那边
Thanks.
谢谢
Let's go.
走吧
- Where are we going?
那我们去哪?
You're going home, aren't you?
你不是要回家吗?
说定了
I'm sorry.
抱歉
The taxi's full.
出租车坐满了
That's cool.
没事
hankvou
- See you tomorrow.
-谢谢－明天见
See you tomorrow.
明天见
You're cruel...
你真狠
Let him marinate a little.
再晾他一会儿
How's Maria Antónia?
玛丽亚·安东尼娅还好吗?
sheokawg
- Come here. Here.
它还好吗？-过来这边
She isn't well toda
She's kind of ill.
它今天不太好有点生病
But she comes here every day
但它每天都来找我
to eat some cardboard.
嚼点纸板
She prefers the oardboard
to anything else.
它宁愿吃纸板也不吃别的
Come here.
过来
Come
来
Come here, Antónia.
过来安东尼娅
Come on.
来嘛
Come here.
过来
Are you married, Bojan?
你结婚了吗布贾那?
Kind of.
算是吧？
Kind of?
算是?
What does that mean?
什么意思?
Me and my wife have some issues.
Issues? Serious or mild?
Family issues.
是家里的事
The first time we got married, I was 23.
我23岁第一次结婚
The first time?
第一次?
Yeah, because then we had a problem
对后来出了点事
and drifted away from each other.
我们就慢慢疏远了
And we got back togethe
when I was already 29.
再复合时我已经29了
I thought you could have three wives.
我还以为你们能娶三个老婆
Is that true?
这是真的吗?
Muslims can have three, even four wives.
穆斯林才可以娶三到四个老婆
But not us animists.
但我们这些泛灵信仰的不行
-Yeah.
-泛灵信仰？-对
What's that?
那是什么？
Take Catholics, for example.
就像天主教那样
They have their own rituals.
他们有自己的仪式
Well, us, animists, also..
我们也一样
performed under kapok trees
也有自己的仪式会在木棉树下
or other large trees
或者别的大树下办
That's where we do everything.
所有事都在那里做
We have this suitcase
with a machine inside
里面有一套设备
to these two machines, Bojan.
要接到这两台机器上布贾那
These are sensors.
这是传感器
They are sensors because they sense.
叫传感器因为它会感应
And how do they sense?
They have this little light here.
它这儿有个小灯
You see?
看到没?
It's called a laser.
这叫激光
When a solid body goes by,
东西一经过…
it sends a signal to this machine,
它就给这台机器发信号
which then takes a picture,
机器会拍一张照片
assuming it's well calibrated,
前提是校准好了的话
and sends it
然后再把照片
to my computer.
传到我电脑上
Animists have their own culture.
泛灵信仰的也有己的化
But their culture also varies
可各族的习俗也不一样
For example, the Balanta people
比如巴兰塔族
have their own way of worshiping,
and performing ceremonies
for their iras
为他们的伊拉神灵举仪式
The Floups have another way.
富鲁比族也有自己的一套
The Mankanyas have yet another wa
of worshiping and their own rituals.
曼坎哈族也有另一套崇拜和仪式
Each ethnicity..
每个族群都不一样
Which is yours?
你是哪一族？
I am Mankanya.
我是曼坎哈族
What other rituals do you perform?
We have the toca-choro, the fanado..
我们有图卡舒霍还有法纳多
What's the toca-choro?
图卡舒霍是什么？
The toca-choro is a ceremony
图卡舒霍是一种仪式
performed for a person, a family member,
给去世的亲人办的
who has passed
perhaps many years ago.
Italso depends
on the status of the family.
也看家里条件
They perform a-ceremonl
in which an animal is sacrificed,
会办一场仪式还得宰一只牲
could be a pig, a cow, though usually
可能是猪也可能是牛
it's a cow
但一般是牛
The cow is sacrifioed
its blood must be spilled.
宰牛时要放血
Its blood honors the dead
the ancestors.
这些血是用来敬奉祖先的
Whether in the toca-choro ceremony
过去不管是图卡舒霍
or for the ira,
还是献给伊拉神灵那种仪式
blood must alwavs be spilled
Even a man,
都一定要流血甚至男人
in order to become a real man,
要成为真正的男人
must lose blood,
也得流血
what we call the fanado
这就是我们说的法纳多
Fanado?
法纳多?
What's the fanado?
法纳多又是什么?
The fanado is a very sacred ritual.
法纳多是一种很神圣的仪式
AllLthe seorets thatl abpenin the wood
stay in the woods.
所有秘密都在林子里发生也只留在林子里
Fuck....
操
Salaam alaikum.
愿你平安
Is it over?
结束了吗?
Not yet?
还没?
Are you having a little break?
你在休息呢?
Bojan.
布贾那
Here's your food.
你的饭来了
Do you eat chicken, Bojan?
布贾那你吃鸡肉吗?
I"II have it without.
我不要鸡肉
Yeah?
-Yes.
-是吗？-对
Do you have any water?
有水吗?
Water?
水?
-Yes.
-有吗？-有
Thanks.
谢谢
Don't do that, Engineer!
喂喂工程师别这么做
to give water to the locals.
Rules are rules.
规矩就是规矩
Look, Engineer, this is on you.
喂工程师你自己看着办出事算你的
But these men are thirsty.
可这些渴得不
The last one who did that got fucked.
上一个这么干的下场很惨
say I didn't know.
行要是出事就说你不知道
Just pretend dunno
You didn't see anything, okay?
就装作你们什么都没看见行吗?
I won't say a word if they ask me.
有人问我我也不会说的
不行真不行
You gotta help your brother, 'cause..
你得帮你兄弟因为…
this is getting ugly, bro
Really ugly.
这事越来越糟兄弟真的很糟
he bosses are fucking us
that's the truth.
老板在狠狠干我们就是这样
There's no other w
without turning us into slaves.
不这样就赚不到钱他们不把人当奴隶就不行
And our job is seriously hard.
They want to banish us
他们想把我们赶走
to some godforsaken desert
and that's bad.
发配到那鸟不拉屎的沙漠这不行真不行
Hurry the fuck up!
快点他妈的
You gotta make a living
哪怕当帮工也行起码得混口饭吃
Is everything okay?
喂亲爱的还好吗?
Good. I'm glad, I'm glad!
好那就好那就好
Do you have plans?
What are you doing tomorrow?
To the movies
Mommy's taking you to the movies?
I wanna go too, I wanna go.
哎我也想去我也想去
I just heard
我刚听说
that my mother-in-law is in the hospital
I wonder how she's doing
我岳母住院了不知道她怎么样了
Give Mommy a big hug and a kiss
I won't be talking to her today.
你替我给妈妈个的拥抱和亲亲吗？我今天不跟她通话了
I'll call later and talk to her.
我晚点再给她打电话
A huge kiss! Bye! Bye, baby.
再给她一个大大的亲亲拜拜拜拜宝贝
I love you.
爱你
When is she having those tests done?
Next month, on the 15th?
嗯？下个月15号?
when's the kid going to school?
那孩子呢？她什么时候上学?
Okay. Next week already? Good.
And how are the olive trees?
橄榄树怎么样?
Laden with olives?
挂满橄榄了吗?
Are there any people to harvest them?
有人来采吗?
That'srea
there's hardly anyone now.
可惜几乎没人了
Do you have a light, Ermínio?
埃尔米尼奥你有打机吗?
Hold on a second.
等我一下
Where are you from, Engineer?
工程师你是从哪来的？
Sorry, Ermínio.
对不起埃尔米尼奥
Please don't call me Engineer.
别叫我工程师
Oh?
哦？
What should I call you, then?
那我该怎么称呼你?
Whatever you like.
随你
Less formally.
别那么正式就好
Do you have a fever?
你发烧了?
I dunno.
不知道
Do you want a whiskey?
来点威士忌吗?
Ain't that bad for you?
那不是对你不好吗?
No!
不
It cleans everything.
能消毒
Maybe Ill have it, then.
那我也来点
Check that out.
你看看
Ciproflox..
环丙沙星
This is antibiotics, man.
这是抗生素兄弟
You can't just take it.
不能随便吃
You'll be right as rain.
吃了就没事
That's the best.
这最好使
It"ll fix you.
对症
When that shit happens to me,
I go straight to SOS mode
你知道我一碰上这种破事就直接去急诊
Straight away
Don't let that reach second stage.
立刻处理别拖到第二阶段
Second stage and you're fucked.
You're finished.
It'll clean your pipes.
你就废了它能把你里外都清干净
You'll be shitting bricks in no time.
很快你会拉稀拉到停不下来
You'll be shitting bricks
and everything else.
拉得像水一样连肠子都要拉出来
You know, a couple of weeks ago
I had malaria.
spentthree days
waiting for a Cuban doctor to be sent
等他们给我派一个古巴医生等了3天
from the main construction site.
从主工地那边
He took his time.
He had some Black woman in labor.
听说那边有难产出血还是什么
Or whatever.
之类的
When he got here.
等人一到
I don't even know what he gave me,
我都不知道他给我打了什么
but it made me crawl outta my skin.
我难受得浑身发痒
I think it was quinine.
我猜是奎宁
Quinine?
I think so.
应该是
It really messed me up.
那玩意儿把我整惨了
And when I entered the cafeteria
the Chinaman saw me,
我一进食堂那个中国人一看见我
it was like he'd seen a ghost.
像见了鬼一样
His eyes widened.
眼睛瞪得老大
Those guys are fucking racist.
那帮人特别种族歧视
We aren't white to them.
在他们眼里我们不算白人
They're even worse with the people
from Senegal and Guinea-Bissau.
对塞内加尔和几内亚比绍的人更狼
Why?
为什么?
When they have an accident
they just throw them in a ditch.
他们一出事就把人扔沟里
And don't notify their families.
连家属都不通知
Man, this is.
兄弟这地方
A slaughterhouse, you might say.
简直是屠宰场
A real slaughterhouse
真正的屠宰场
But what really bothers me
可我最受不了的
is that Black people are the worst.
是黑人也最狠
They're even racist to each other.
他们对自己也搞种族歧视
How did you end up here?
你怎么跑到这来的?
Well. those of us with no skills
must make ends meet.
我这种啥也不会的人只能出来讨生活
I'm surprised about you
a young guy, educated.
让我吃惊的反倒是你年轻又有文化
Couldn't you find a job?
Or you like adventure?
找不到作？还是你就爱冒险?
Thought you were gonna get rich?
That this was EI Dorado,
还是以为这里能发财这地方就是黄金国?
that money grew on trees?
以为钱能长在树上?
Maybe
- No, man..
-也许吧-不兄弟
isten, if you want my advice
get outta here.
听我一句劝赶紧走
No one cares about this shit.
这地方谁也不在乎
Go ahead, Ermínio
来吧埃尔米尼奥
Gimme the meat.
把肉给我
I"Il do it.
我来
I want mine well done, okay?
- Good old Joca!
If there's anyone brave enough
to do it..
要是有人够胆干
Some people here are trying to help.
有人想帮忙
- It's all talk but they do nothing.
-也有人只会嘴上说-说了也不干
Look at him.
你看看他
You need teach you
how to build a fire?
你生火还得让水手教你?
Hey.
嘿
To what do we owe this luxury?
怎么会有这么好的待遇的?
Join us, man
过来一起吃吧
I'm celebrating my-daughter
Patricia's birthday, she's 17 now.
我今天在这给我过她叫帕特西娅刚满17岁了
Happy birthday.
生日快乐
and I haven't seen her in three years.
在葡萄牙我已经3年没能陪她了
to have a little celebration.
所以我在这边办个小小的庆祝
- It's a little late.
-做点开心的事-有一点点晚了
Join us, have some meat.
来吧吃点肉
-No, I'm good. Thanks.
-坐吧-我没事不用了谢谢
ave
- If you want a cold one..
-喝一杯-想喝冰的就说
Amberme
- I"Il take it.
-琥珀甘露－我来一瓶
I"Il join you.
我陪你们
Bring him
- Something to eat?
-拿个杯子给他-吃点?
No, thanks, I'm good.
不用谢谢我没事
Taste this meat, it's really good.
尝尝这肉真不错
Thank you, I'm okay.
Next time we're having pork steaks too.
下次还有猪排
Oh yeah?
- Yeah.
-真的吗？-对
Let me know
- AIll right.
-到时候通知我-行
- All right.
She's 17, my princess.
我家小公主17岁了
A brilliant mind, like yours.
脑子很灵跟你一样
- She cares about the world.
-不-还总替这世界操心
the polar bears, the mosquitoes.
说要拯救鲸鱼北极熊还有蚊子
kids care about nowadays.
现在孩子就爱关心这些
she's got her mother's brains.
还好她的聪明劲随她妈
Bojan, are you okay?
布贾那你没事吧?
Yeah.
没事
Everything all right at home?
家里都好吗?
Yeah.
都好
You sure?
你确定?
Yeah.
确定
Youmean vou'renotworrie
about what's happening right now?
就是说你不担眼下这些事?
No.
不担心
I heard that in Bojan's village
我听说在布贾那的村子
regarding our work here.
出了点事还牵扯到我们这份活
Is that true, Bojan?
是真的吗布贾那?
Problems happen all the time.
麻烦天天有
Right.
是啊
But_there ar
different kinds of problems.
可麻烦也分轻重
Some are more serious than others
有的更严重
and have greater consequences.
tseems vour wife and-kids
are among the leaders
听说你婆和孩子算是带头的那批
fighting against
the construction of this road.
在反对修这条路
I don't know if that's true.
我也不知道真假
People talk..
反正大家都在说
working here now
When I get home, we'll see.
我先在这边干活回去再说
We each have our own way of thinking.
每个人想法不一样
Young people might favo
constructing the road.
年轻人可能支持修路
Old people and farmers
aren't gonna like it,
老人和农民肯定不乐意
use they'll lose some of the land
they usually work on
他们会丢掉平时耕的地就是他们赖以干活的那地
on behalf of development, let's say.
就算说是为了发展
ration
development.
发展这词太沉了
Some people want it,
有人想要
eep
the life they had before.
也有人只想过原来的日子
forfarming
they're gonna lose it.
守着田地原本能种地的那片田也要没了
What will happen to those people?
那他们以后怎么办?
Whatever...
算了
What about those sardines?
- They're in the freezer.
-沙丁鱼还有吗？-在冰柜里
They're just for us, right?
那是给我们吃的吧?
Just for us, they get nothing.
只给我们他们不吃
Let's have some sardines!
来吃沙丁鱼吧
Do you like frozen sardines?
你爱吃冻沙丁鱼吗?
I don't mind.
When there's no alternative.
有得吃就行
don't like frozen
I'd rather have them grilled!
Not frozen.
冻的不行
What is this shit?
这什么鬼?
Ousmane!
奥斯曼
Ousmane, come here right now!
奥斯曼立刻给我过来
What the fuckis this?
这他妈什么东西?
What is this doing in the freezer?
这玩意儿为什么在冰柜里?
I dunno.
不知道
You don't know?
你不知道?
Aren't you in charge of food?
你不是管食物的吗?
I dunno.
不知道
'ou've mixed this
with our croquettes, asshole?
你就拿这玩意儿拌进我们的炸丸子里？你个狗东西
What's going on?
- Are you trying to kill us?
-怎么了？-你想害死我们吗？
Are these assholes trying to kill us?
这帮狗娘养的想害死我们吗?
Have you seen this?
你们看见了吗?
Come here! Check this out!
过来过来看看
This asshole's trying to kill us!
这狗东西就是想害死我们
ook at what he's putting
with our croquettes.
看看他往我们的炸丸子里放什么
Look at this!
就在我们冰柜里你们看
Easy, Joao! Take it easy.
冷静若昂冷静点
You're fucked.
狗娘养的
Easy, Joao. This is mine.
冷静若昂这是我的
This is yours?
- Yes, I put it there.
You put this in here?
是你把它放进去的?
Yes, these are samples
My freezer broke down.
对这些是样品我自己的冰柜坏了
It's not a big deal.
这东西没问题
Couldn't you put it somewhere else?
那你就没别的地方放?
You had to put it in the freezer
next to our food?
非得挨着我们的吃的放?
What are you, a moron?
你是不是有病?
This is sealed, it's okay
You can eat it.
I'm not eating any of that shit!
You think I'm gonna eat that?
你自己去吃
You can't put that next to our food!
你不能把这东西跟吃的放一起
You can't just do
whatever you please here.
也别在这儿想干嘛就干嘛
You're right. I'm sorry.
你说得对对不起
How doI know there's not
a virus in there? A bacteria, whatever!
谁知道会不会带上什么病毒细菌乱七八糟的
Calm down, Joǎo
- Fucking moron!
-冷静点若昂-真他妈蠢
My God
I've had it up to here with you!
天啊我真受够你了
I'm getting fucking tired of you!
我越来越受够你了
Tired!
受够了
Calm down, Joǎo.
冷静若昂
Calm down?
I've been way too calm with you.
我冷静？我对你已经够冷静了
Ever since you got here,
you've been ignoring me,
你从来这里开始就当我不存在
stepping on me
disrespecting me,
踩着我不尊重我
and now you wantme
to accept your apologies?
现在还想要我接受你的道歉?
I'm gonna be as polite
as I possibly can.
行我尽量客气点告诉你
Shove your apologies up your ass!
把你的道歉塞你屁眼
Calm down, Joǎo
Think of your daughter.
冷静若昂想想你女儿
Don't talk about my daughter!
别提我女儿
You just fucked up her birthday party
你他妈的刚把我的派对搅黄了
and you're fucking talking about her?
你还好意思提她?
It's all right, trust me.
没事相信我
It's not all right!
To you, everything's always fine.
I should beat the crap outta you!
天啊我真想狠狠干你一顿
One day your luck will run out.
你迟早要倒霉
You don't wanna be alone in the dark.
你不想一个人待在黑里吧
Take it easy
- Take this as friendly advice.
-别冲动-当我好心提醒
Remember what happened
to your Italian predecessor,
别忘了你那意大利前任的下场
who's six feet under right now.
他坟头都长草了
Don't do anything
you might regret, Joao.
Don't let the same thing
happen to you.
当心别落得跟他一样
And now get the fuck outta here!
现在给我滚出去
You already fucked up my daughter's
birthday party, motherfucker!
你把我的派对毁了你个畜
I"II fucking get you for this!
这事我跟你没完
Fuck!
操
What's going on?
Engineer Sérgio
put some bags in the freezer.
That's what caused all this.
就因为这个
Okay, put that away.
行把它拿走
Sit down.
坐吧
Is this a wake, or what?
怎么了这是在办丧事吗?
Let's keep the party going!
来吧继续庆祝
We'd better.
我看行
bring that over here
so we can toast!
把那个拿来我们来干杯
Ermínio!
埃尔米尼奥
- Let's make a toast!
-来干一杯-咱们要敬酒
Gather round.
都过来
To my dauqhter
and our families back home!
敬我女儿帕特里西娅还有家里人
A toast!
干杯
Let go! Let me go!
放开我放开
Let me go!
放开
What's going on over there?
那边怎么了?
Come here! Come!
过来过来
These fuckers can't handle alcohol.
Stay out of it, sir!
先生别插手
Then they come here and fuck up.
然后跑来这闹事
Just looking for trouble.
就是找茬
Come here, you fucking Portuguese!
过来你这葡萄牙废物
Stay out of it, sir!
先生别插手
Come here!
过来
I'm gonna rip out your hair!
我把你头发薅光
Come on! Come here!
来啊过来
What the hell's going on here?
这里到底怎么了?
I have no problem with you.
我不跟你过不去
I just wanna kill him!
我只想杀了他
Hamedna, listen to me
In here, every problem is my problem.
Let me go. I'm gonna kill him.
放开我我要杀了他
He will be punished
and pay you handsomely, okay?
他会受罚也会赔你一笔行吗?
I'm gonna do to him what he did to me.
不我不要钱我只要讨回他对我做的事
No, let me go!
不放开我
If you hit him, you'll go to jail,
你打他你就要坐牢
but if you hit me
nothing happens to you.
可你打我你就没事
Let me go!
放开我
No, listen!
If you hit him, you'll go to jail.
不听我说你打他就得坐牢
I told you!
我说了
Let me go!
- Hit me!
-放开我-打我啊
Let me go!
- Me!
-放开我-打我
Hit me!
- I'm telling you to let go!
-打我啊-我叫你放手
Let me go!
You, come here!
放开我你过来
Hit me, Hamedna!
打我啊哈梅德纳
Let me go!
放开我
- Get outta here!
－放开-滚出去
Come here!
过来
and you'll see!
你敢跑你就等着
Come here!
过来
过来啊
We all need to get some air.
家都得出去透透气
and go to the club.
别磨叽了去酒吧
Sérgio!
塞尔吉奥
but I never hold a grudge, okay?
你要知道我脾是急但不爱记仇吧?
Ne shouldn'tlet thatshit
ruin our relationship.
别把关系搞僵
We're professioi
we must work together.
我们是同事得一起干活
Come with u
Best thing you can get here.
来跟我们走我请你喝杯米酿是这儿最好的
Alright?
行吗?
Okay.
行
Come on, man.
走吧兄弟
Let's go.
走
What was that about the Italian?
你刚说那意利怎么回事?
There are lots of theories.
说法很多
arouno
with a local Black girl
他跟我说他爱上了一个村的黑妹
and wanted to take her to Europe.
想带她去欧洲
He even wanted to divorce his wife.
还想跟老婆离婚
Except she wouldn't let him
and he never got his visa.
可她不肯离他也一直办不下签证
I knew him well.
我跟他很熟
We went out drinking a few times.
一起喝过几次酒
Now it's a whole thing.
现在事情闹大了
lfyou ask me
he ran off with the Black girl.
我看他八成就是跟那黑妹跑了
Who's never thought of it?
A pretty little Black girl.
谁能想到他会跟个漂亮小黑妹跑
Careful..
小心
He's either drunk or dead.
这家伙是醉了还是死了?
it the fuoking gas!
- Watch out!
-有毒气-小心
Don't stop, it's an ambush!
别停是埋伏
You'll see 10 or 20 guys
come down from the hills!
你会看见上冲下来10到20个
Watch out!
- He's either drunk or dead!
-小心小心-他要么醉了要么死了
Stop! Don't!
停车别
Stop the car!
停车啊
Stop the car! Stop!
停车停
They can't fool me!
Don't stop, man!
他们这招骗不了我别停兄弟
They"l kill us!
他们会弄死我们
Stop the fucking car!
Stop the car!
给我停车停车
He was all packed, man.
他东西都打包好了兄弟
He was all paek
to run off with her.
早就准备好带她跑
he side
of the road with their belongings.
后来他们在路边找到了车还有那堆证件
Who knows what happened.
谁知道后来发生了什么
What can we drink?
有什么喝的?
Don't you have anything stronger?
Do you understand?
听懂没?
Stronger.
更烈的
Melissa!
梅丽莎
Are you okay?
你没事吧?
Really okay?
真没事?
You're gonna try some rice spirit.
你得尝点米酒
Beer's fine.
我喝啤酒就行
Forget the beer
You're having some rice spirit.
别喝啤酒喝点米酒
No, no, no.
不不不
Rice spirit.
Is this it?
就这个?
A little bit.
一点点
That's enough.
够了
All right?
Thank you.
从哪里来的?
听不懂?
Well?
怎么样?
好喝吗?
Yeah, it's good.
嗯不错
Go easy on it, 'cause...
你慢点喝
that stuffs strong.
这酒后劲很大
For him too.
给他也来一瓶
No, no.
不不
Yes, yes.
来来给他
Him too.
他也要
一点点就醉了醉了醉了
Thanks.
A little bit.
一点点
你好吗?
我挺好你呢?
我就在这儿
就我一个
我觉得还行
你觉得?
你会说英语吗?
你会说法语吗?
A little, yeah.
嗯会一点
We can speak French, then.
好
Do you understand what I'm saying?
-Yeah, I do.
Loud and clear.
清清楚楚
But my French is "small."
但我法语很烂
I think you can handle it.
I dunno.
我不知道
你也可以说英语随你
你来这就是为了这个对吧?
你到底怎么回事?
你想待在这里吗?
你为什么要来这?
不我做不了
出去
Get out!
滚
Come on!
走吧
我做不了
那就别做
然后呢?
那你至少能让己兴奋下吗?
So we can get this over with?
这样我们就能结束了
我会试试
Your colleague paid for it,
but not for the whole night.
你同事付了钱但没付包夜的费用
You think what I care about?
你觉得我在乎什么?
What do you care about?
你在乎什么？嗯?
Working condition for sex workers?
在乎性工作者的工作环境吗?
The well-being of women in this country?
在乎这个国家女性的福祉吗?
Human trafficking, maybe ?
人贩子问题?
Minimum Wage?
还是最低工资?
You care about that?
你在乎那些吗?
Clean water for everyone?
每个人都能喝到干净水吗?
Is that what you care about?
你在乎这些吗?
I wish I could be like you.
我希望我能像你一样
You have no idea what it's like to be me.
你根本不明白做我这样的感受
我不装作在乎
是啊或许这就是区别所在
我在乎是的我在乎
你在乎的是你自己
只在乎你自己舒服不舒服
只在乎去妓院之后还装得道貌岸然
你在乎的就这些对吧?
What disgusts me the most..
我最恶心的就是
are good men.
一个好男人
我不明白你在说什么
我最恶心的是什么？一个好男
像你这样
Excuse me.
打扰一下
I just need you to open this.
我想让你帮我把这个打开
Hold on, I'm coming.
等下我来了
II do it.
我来了
Look how precious!
This is the face of wealth!
看看多金贵这就是有钱人的脸
This is for you.
给你的
Now I'm into your trip.
我现在开始喜欢这趟行程了
Look at how long it is,
你看这有多大
how well it's gonna fit.
多合适
I love it. Help me, girl, please.
我太爱了姐们帮我一下
Hold on, I"ll get down.
等等 我蹲下
you should braid your hair, love.
不过我觉得你得编辫子亲爱的
Okay, but now Ijust wanna see
how I feel
哎对可我现在就想体验下这种感觉
Hold on.
等等
Like this
-Put it on, that's it.
Come on.
来
Where's the rubber band?
皮筋在哪儿?
Here.
在这
I'm not gonna lie.
我想你想疯了不骗你
I missed you like crazy.
我真是太想你了
Can you put this away?
你能把这个收起来吗?
Put it over there, please
Can you put them on display?
麻烦放到展架上
This too
这个也要
Take this suitcase.
拿上这个箱子
-Look who's here.
-别紧张-看看谁来了
Good afternoon!
下午好
We thouahtyou were getting your
things out, but it seems you aren't.
我们以为你在收拾东西看来没有
Getting my things for what?
You've been informed that this plac
has a new owner.
这地方换老板了
This place?
That's impossible.
这地方换老板了？不可能吧
We've been instructed by our boss
老板让我们来
to ask
when you'll be handing it over.
问你什么时候交出来
What boss are you talking about
- Our boss.
-你说的老板是谁？-我们老板
handing over the place today.
老板说你今天就得交房
-I won't hand over this place.
没得谈-我不会交的
Do you know this place?
那块地方是我的你知道这地方吗?
'cause I spoke to your superior
我不懂因为我跟你们上头谈过
and he said everything
was taken care of.
他说都处理好了
I'm not following
- Our superior?
-我听不懂-我们上头?
Im really confuse
- Who's our superior?
-我更糊涂了-我们上头是谁?
there's nothing to talk about.
该关门了没什么好谈
- Plus, you've got debts to pay.
-不夫人-再说你还欠债
Yes.
-我还欠债？-对
Buddy
to your superior
兄弟我说了我找过你们上头的人了
who said everything was taken care of.
他说都处理好了
Now you tell me I have debts.
现在你们又说我欠债
You see this place?
你看看这地方?
This is a place that welcomes
very important people from Bissau.
这地专门接待比绍来的物
Okay, but we're giving you three months
to hand over the place.
行那我们给你3个月交出来
That's notpossibl
-Ma'am!
Yes
-是-夫人
It's time to close
and leave this place
该关门了你得走
We came here twice
you must hand over the place today.
我们来过两次你今天必须交
You see that mango tree over there?
你看到那边那棵芒果树了吗?
Do vou see it?
-Yes.
-看见了吗？-看见了
My great-grandmother
planted that mango tree.
No one in this country
will take me away from here.
这国家没人能把我赶走
I've already told you
I spoke to your superior
我早说了我跟你们上面的人谈过
and he said
everything's taken care of.
他也说都解决了
This mango tree is my peace of mind
my shade.
这棵芒果树就是我的安身处也是我乘凉的树荫
This place is all I have.
我就剩这地方
Nobody is gonna take me away from here.
谁也别想把我赶走
I beg you to let me work in peace.
求你们让我安静做生意
Let me make a living.
让我讨口饭吃
The man vou spoke to deoeived voi
- Please get outta my place.
-你和他说话的那个人骗了你-请你们从我地盘撤走
You can't kick us out!
You're the ones kicking me out.
是你们在赶我走啊
You came twice
I told you it was solved.
你们来过两次我都说解决了
You didn't bring any documents.
You brought nothing!
你们没带任何文件什么都没有
Where's the document
saying I owe you?
You got nothing!
你们什么都没有
Excuse me, buddy.
兄弟请吧
Well
- Let's go.
－好-我们走
Good evening
- Hello. How are you?
Who are you?
Me?
- I'm kidding!
－我？－我开玩笑的
You startled me
What happened to your bar?
吓我一跳你的酒吧怎么了?
It's complicated, never mind
-What?
-说来话长算了-什么?
Come in
- Can I?
-进来－我能进吗?
Sure.
- Thanks.
当然-谢谢
You can sit down.
Okay.
好
Would you like something to drink?
想喝点什么？
Do you have any tea
Do you know how to make it?
你有茶吗知道怎么泡吗?
If I can make tea?
如果我会泡的话?
Warga.
瓦尔加
Warga? You drink warga?
瓦尔加？你喝瓦尔加?
I like it.
我喜欢
You know that's a heavy drug.
你知道那是烈性毒品吗？
Sorry. I was..
抱歉我刚才…
I was looking at your incense.
在看你的香
I noticed
注意到了
Lucky, huh?
挺走运啊
We have gas.
有煤气了
I hope I'm not interrupting anything.
希望我没打扰你
I wouldn't call it interrupting.
不算打扰
Do you wanna ask me
a more direct question?
Were you doing anything
before I got here?
我来之前你在做什么?
Yes
- What?
-是-在做什么?
Braiding my hair.
在编头发
Sorry, I don't like to see
disheveled hair
抱歉头发一乱我就难受我就顺顺
Now you're fine.
现在好多了
Deluxe, by Diára.
这杯是迪娅拉的豪华款
You thinkit's funny?
-Yeah.
-你觉得好笑？-嗯
This is the best tea
you'll ever have.
这是你喝过最好的茶
Told you.
我早就说了
You're absolutely right.
千真万确
I missed it.
我早就在想了
You want some more?
-谢谢-不客气
Do you need anything?
I need to get some rest.
我得休息了
It's late.
太晚了
Wait. What happened?
I wanna get some rest.
我想休息
We can talk some other time.
那我们改天再聊
I'd like to ask you some questions.
我想问你点事
What about?
问什么?
About you.
问你
About me?
问我?
Let life answer them.
让生活自己回答吧
I really need to get some rest now.
我现在真的要休息了
Thank you.
谢谢
Bye, thanks for the tea
Don't mention it.
-谢谢你的茶-不客气
Good night.
晚安
What is this?
这是什么?
Goat meat.
羊肉
You just leave it here for a while?
What's in it?
面放了什么?
What do you put in it?
你都放了什么?
Onions...
洋葱…
Sérgio.
塞尔吉奥
What?
怎么了?
Oh, man... What the fuck?
天啊这他妈怎么回事?
This is gonna be a bloodbath.
要血流成河了
A good killer sheds no blood.
下手干净就不见血
Look at its face.
你看看那张脸
Stop it, Sérgio.
Think we could buy one, and save it?
别闹塞尔吉奥我们买一只救下来行不行?
-Just go crazy and do it.
-Now?
-就豁出去干吧-现在?
Buy one and save it.
买一只救下来
Let's ask how much it is.
去问问多少钱
I"Il go ask!
我去问
50,000,65,55
- Okay.
-5万到6万5-好
Okay.
好
Listen
- What?
－听着-什么?
I think one is 50,000,
他说一只要5万那边那只好像就是
but there's a more expensive one.
但还有更贵的
He said between 50, 60, 65..
他说5万到6万5
He said some goats cost 120,000.
还有母羊要12万
Would you save the poorest?
那你救最便宜的吗?
That's another problem, right?
I'm gonna save the cheapest.
这是个问题对吧？我现在就救最便宜的
The world is full of problems.
这世界问题一堆
The cheapest or most expensive?
Or the one in the middle.
救最便宜的还是最贵的还是中间那只?
Or the sweetest?
还是最甜的那只?
Just by looking
which one would you save?
只看眼你会救哪只?
Iwouldn't save the white one.
- That's another..
-白的我不救-但这又是另一回事
No? All right.
-我不救白的-不救吗？行吧
Not at all!
绝对不救
But it's also... The poor thing. Why?
可的也挺可怜的为啥不救?
No, I wouldn't save the white one.
不我不救白的朋友
There's a whole history with whites
that should be explained to her
but I'm not a goat to do so.
但我又不是山羊不能给它解释
Fine. What about the other three?
- I'd save the black one, obviously.
-行那另外三只呢-我当然救黑的那只
Which must be the most expensive
'cause she's big, fat.
那只可能最贵因为又大又肥
What do you think?
- It should be the most expensive.
-你觉得呢-我觉得那只最贵
I dunno, man.
哎我也不确定兄弟
The youngest.
最年轻的吧
Beautiful!
-就救最年轻的-挺漂亮
Difficult choice.
- I think it's beautiful.
-真难选-我觉得那只很漂亮
Because she'll live longer
than the oldest.
She's lived less, right?
可她活得更少对吧?
But just imagine
if we decided our lives this way.
但想想我们用这种方式决定生死
The youngest gets to live,
the oldest dies.
就像年轻的活老的死
We could dance a little tango.
我们可以在这跳段探戈
Shake our booties
- A tango, here? Let's do it.
-扭扭屁股-在这跳探戈吗？来啊
No, it was a stupid suggestion.
算了这主意挺蠢
How do you dance the tango?
That's not it.
探戈怎么跳？不是那样
This is the tango.
这才是探戈
Girl!
姑娘
Don't do that.
别这么跳
You have to lead, I'm the lady.
-I know.
-你得带着我我是女士-我知道
Is this it?
这样吗?
Thank you
-Thanks.
-谢谢-多谢
Are you going out today?
-Yes.
-你今晚要出去吗？-要啊
I'm going clubbing with Diára.
我要和迪娅拉去夜店
I think she's turning in, no?
She's not.
她才没有
Think you know her better than me
I'm her best friend.
你觉得你比我更了解她吗？我才是她最好的朋友
She told me that and kicked me out.
她说要睡觉还把我轰走了
She lied to you
perhaps she wanted you gone.
她骗你可能就是想让你
How do you know she lied?
你怎么知道她骗了你?
That's my perception, in my head.
我就是这么感觉的
She told me she was turning in
她跟我说要睡了
and kicked me out of her house.
然后把我从她家轰出去
mustive done something
for her to do that,
你肯定做了什么她才会那样
Dlara
wouldn't do that for no reason.
迪娅拉不会无缘无故这么做
Unless you deserve it or like it.
除你活该或者你就爱这样
Yeah, I love it.
对我就爱
won't judge
- I love being kicked out.
-有人就喜欢也别说他-我就爱被轰走
I actually see you in that position.
我还真能想象你那副样子
Okay, I'm going.
行我走了
ask ifyou can go,
because..
我去问迪娅拉你能不能去
No, no!
别别
She didn't want to.
怎么不行？她不是不想
Please, don't tell her I'm coming.
别求你别说我要去
Of course not. It's a surprise.
当然不说给她个惊喜
She loves surprises.
她就爱惊喜
doesnltknow you know
I've been at her house.
可她不知道你已经知道我去过她家
wentto see her?
- She didn't tell you!
-你去见过她了？-她没跟你说吗?
secrets?
Because she and I are friends
你倒是会保密可我和她是朋友
-And you're keeping a secret
- No, but she was gonna tell you.
-结果你还瞒着我-没有她本来要告诉你的
What happened this afternoon?
Nothing. It wasn't in the afternoon,
it was now.
I was there just now.
我刚刚就在那
Doing what?
去干嘛?
Well, I was visiting a friend,
someone I like.
就是去看个朋友一个我喜欢的
But yeah.
-Whatever.
I told her to meet me at Sabura
in 20 minutes.
我约她20分钟后在萨布拉见
If you wanna come
she can kick you out again.
如果你想来，她还能再把你轰出去一次
I'll go, I'll go.
我去我去
Hey, snooty!
喂自大狂
Where's your phone?
- I was getting ready!
-你手机呢？-我刚才在准备呢！
For 30 minutes?
- I'm sorry!
-准备了30分钟吗？-对不起?
You're sorry?
你还好意思说对不起?
Look who's here
- Hello!
-看谁来了？－嗨
Hi!
嗨
What are you doing here?
你来这干嘛?
- I'm not the one who was turning in
- Well, the tea kept me up.
-我可没说我要睡 - 嗯 都怪那茶 害我失眠了
Shall we?
走吧?
Let's go.
走走
How are you?
你好吗?
How are you doing?
你过得怎么样?
I'm good.
挺好
Good to see you.
见到你真好
How's it going?
- Breezy?
-你好吗？-布里兹?
Hello
- Good evening.
-你好-晚上好
Sérgio, right?
-Yes.
-Sérgio对吧? －素
Wanna come?
- I"Il be right back.
-要一起吗？-我马上回来
Wait.
Can't you stay with me for a bit?
等等你不能陪我几分钟吗?
I'Il take it.
我来
pect
to see you guys together.
没想到你们会在一起
Have you known each other long?
你们是朋友吗？认识很久了?
We're friends.
我们是朋友
I advise you to be careful.
我劝你小心点
sensed some chemistry
am I right?
我闻到点火花对吧?
If you look the Medusa in the eye,
she'll explode at you.
Hold on, what chemistry? Careful?
等等什么火花小心什么？？
With the Medusa.
对着美杜莎
When you look the Medusa in the eye..
你直视美杜莎的时候
She'll explode all over your face.
她会在你脸上炸开
You don't know the city
or what's going on.
你不懂这座城也不知道发生了什么
It's messed up
to talk about a friend like that.
你这么说我朋友有点恶心了
I'm telling you because she's my friend.
兄弟别紧张她是我朋友我才提醒你
You don't have to be aggressive.
你不用这么冲
I didn't mean it like that.
我不是那个意思
It was a joke, bro.
我开玩笑的兄弟
to take it easy, that's all.
我就是让你放轻松就这意思
Nothing more, okay?
没别的深意行吗?
Are you offering romantic advice?
你在给我感情建议吗?
Romantic advice? Nah, bro.
感情建议？不至于兄弟
Im just saying that you're
in an exotic place, you become.
我只是说你到了个陌生地方
emotionally involved
everything's exciting and exotic..
情绪会被带着走看什么都新鲜
L'm-iust-sa .take it easy
I didn't mean to offend you.
我跟你说真的别急我不是想冒犯你
Ithouqht your mone
would reduce your coarseness.
我还以为你有钱就不会这么粗野
You got me wrong.
行兄弟抱歉你误会我了
Ididn'tmean to invade
your privacy.
我没想闯进你生活也没想窥探你的隐私
It's your life, man.
这是你的人生兄弟
It's all right
Listen, we're having fun.
没事听着我们是出来玩的
You look tense.
你太紧张了
Let's have a drink and start over.
喝一杯重新来
Let's start over.
重新来
A toast to a consequential life.
为一段有分量的人生干杯
I know being here isn't easy.
我知道在这不容易
now it's not exactly
what you thought it would be
也知道这里不是你想象的那样
you get here and see
a lot of contradictions and.
你一来就看到一堆麻烦事
it can get under your skin.
我也说不准可能会刺到你
You look at someone like me,
你看着像我这样的人
with money, a good house
a good car
有钱有房有车
the poverty
the shit, the stench, the rottenness.
你走上街就看到贫穷狗屎臭味腐烂
You go to my house
you see my family, you see me and..
你到我家看到我家人看到我…
Everything's wrong and we're the source
of all this shit, right?
你觉得切都不对这堆烂事的源头就是我们对吧?
"primitive accumulation of capital" is?
原始资本积累你知道是什么吗?
Brother, when you think about Europe,
兄弟你想想欧洲
that civilized, structured Europe,
那个文明有秩序的欧洲
with its magnificent cathedrals..
还有那些宏伟的大教堂
You dom
running down the walls.
你看不到墙上流下来的血
Architecture, engineering
medicine..
建筑工程医学
Blood ane
and more blood.
都是血更多的血
Constant disruption, and rebuilding
Constant reformulation.
不断断裂不断重建不断改写不断交换
Constant power exchanges.
权力不断更替
Borders built, then taken apart.
边界先被划出又被拆掉
In the name of God!
都打着上帝的名义
Absolute barbarism.
彻头彻尾的野蛮
How do you think someone
你觉得这些怎么能
can control the cement,
控制水泥?
control the media,
怎么能控制媒体?
control telecommunications?
怎么能控制电信?
Who arn eople?
Where did they come from?
这些是谁他们怎么变成这样的?
ittake
to establish them?
建这套东西要多久?
We'd need several millennia
to compete with them.
我们得花几千年才能跟他们竞争
We will get crushed without.
不然我们会被直接碾碎
any tolerance.
毫无余地
who bears hospitals in mind.
想想看医院掌握在谁?
when structurally nothing's missing.
所谓团结很容易因为结构都在那
So I ask you: how will we provide
three meals a day?
所以我问你我们怎么保证一日三餐?
The best way to get calcium
in your body is by drinking milk.
Semi-skimmed cow milk.
牛奶半脱脂全脂
vare people supposed to think
on an empty stomach?
肚子空的人还有心思想这些吗?
How is someone
who can't guarantee a meal
连一顿饭都保证不了的人
supposed to articulate a thought?
还能组织语言 组织思想吗?
Who's in charge of progress?
谁能推进事情?
[
The elites
Those with time to think,
是精英 那些有时间思考的人
to organize, and plan,
是那些有时间思考 有时间组织 有时间规划的人
are the only ones
who can offer a possibility.
只有他们才能给出可能性
There are no guarantees,
no guarantees.
没保证 没保证
At what cost?
那代价呢?
That's somaething
you have to live with.
这代价我们得扛着
Or do nothing instead.
不然就什么都不做
Join the barbarism of doing nothing,
加入那种什么都不做的野蛮人
believing that it is organic,
that it happens.
去相信它自然发生
Consider that what
we're trying to do here
想想我们在这想做的事
is exactly what they did over there,
其实就是他们那边做过的
except with less blood, less brutality
只是少点血腥少点残酷
and in a shorter period of time.
时间也更短
Not everything's decided
or articulated.
不是每件事都能被决定或被说清
Yes, people are qonna die,
they will suffer, it will hurt.
对 会死人 会受苦 会阵痛
How could this be done without pain?
Can you tell me?
可不痛怎么做 你告诉我?
Without pain or blood?
不流血怎么成?
If  we keep waiting for a code,
I dunno..
你还在等什么代码吗?
of truth..
所谓真理的代码
of truth....
If we keep expecting...
要是一直期待
a sense of collective embrace.
一种集体的拥抱感
We're talking about capital,
我们说的是资本
market, private enterprise.
市场经济，私营企业
That's you.
那就是你
What?
什么?
That's you.
就是你
Me?
-Yes.
-我吗？-是
It's us. It's us.
我们是我们
Those who want to change the world,
想把世界变一变
deconstruct what's wrong
把坏的拆开
and figure out
what can effect a new reality...
再拼出新的现实
Progress.
进步
Why not?
It's one way of looking at things.
为什么不呢？这也是一种看法
Progress, sure
- It's blackmail.
-进步 当然-这就是勒索
It's got nothing to do with blackmail.
这跟勒索没关系
Imagine the world...
- Blackmail.
-想象一下世界-是勒索
Listen!
听着
Eternal.
永恒
We didn't make that decision.
这规则不是我们定的
It was over there.
是在那边定的
They made the rules,
and signed the contracts.
他们定规则 签合同
They drew the lines.
在那边划的法律
That's enough, buddy.
别得寸进尺，亲
Thanks, that's okay
I'm gonna dance with my friends.
谢谢 没事 我去跟我朋友跳舞
Stop it!
别跳了
Stop!
Please, Stop!
- That's our song, girl!
-求你了 别跳了-那是我们的歌姑娘
That's our song.
那是我们的歌
I fucking told you to stop!
我他妈让你别跳了
I woke up at dawn
To chase the dough
天一亮就起床去赚钱
Working the streets
To take it home
在街上干活 把钱带回家
I was born poor
But I'm gonna die rich
我生来贫穷 但我要富着死
Life's not for the faint of heart
人生不属于胆小鬼
I woke up at dawn
To chase the dough
天一亮就起床去赚钱
Working the streets
To take it home
在街上干活 把钱带回家
I was born poor
But I'm gonna die rich
人生来贫穷但我要富着死
Every morning
My mother grows older
每天早上 我妈又老了一点
She eats the sweat of my brow
她靠我流的汗而活着
I haven't been a good son
我不是个好儿子
Father-God, I kneel before you
天父我跪在你面前
Lord, light up my life
主啊照亮我的人生
Bring peace to my life
给我的生活带来安宁
I want to be a good dealer
我想当个好庄家
I want to have a lotta diamonds
我想要一堆钻石
I want to have a lotta passports
我想要一堆护照
I want to step on every continent
我想踏遍每一块大陆
What the fuck do you want?
你他妈想干什么?
你他妈想要什么?
This is me. I'm getting off
到了 我下车了
Marcelina!
玛塞丽娜
Coming!
来
I can take you home.
我可以送你回家
I'll drop you off at home.
我把你送到家
No.
不用
Then let me stay with you awhile.
那让我陪你一会
I don't wanna be alone,
this was messed up.
我不想一个人 这事太糟了
Is that all right?
可以吗?
No.
不可以
Why?
为什么？
Because No.
不为什么
Horácio.
奥拉西奥
Sérgio.
塞尔吉奥
I'm sorry to call vou like this
and being in here,
抱歉我这么叫 你还跑到这里
but would you like to join me
or wait 20 minutes?
你要不要跟我一起 还是等20分钟我结束?
I'Il join you.
我陪你
Great.
好
I was worried, you know?
我很担心你知道吗?
I hope so.
I also wanted to talk to you.
希望是这样 我也想跟你谈谈
You wanted to talk to me?
你想跟我谈?
Great, I'm here. What is it?
好说吧什么事?
What happened to Leonardo?
莱昂纳多怎么了？
Excuse me?
什么?
Leonardo.
莱昂纳多
You knew him well, didn't you?
你跟莱昂纳多很熟 对吧
What do you mean?
什么叫莱昂纳多怎么了?
I got a feeling
you have something to tell me.
我感觉你有话要对我说
That's it.
就是这个
What do you think happened to him?
你觉得莱昂纳多怎么了?
I don't know.
不知道
I'd like to know.
我也想知道
I called you  here
'cause we need to talk.
我叫你来是因为我们有些事要谈
About some unfinished business, no?
谈点没了结的事 对吧?
Why did he take so long
to deliver the report?
他为什么拖了那么久才交报告?
What happened in the meantime?
这期间发生了什么?
When did you last see him?
你最后次见他是什么时候?
Is this an interrogation?
这是在审讯我吗?
What do you think
happened to Leonardo?
你觉得莱昂纳多怎么了?
Do you think
he might've been murdered?
你觉得他有可能被杀了吗？
You know the relationship we had?
你知道我跟莱昂纳多是什么关系吗?
How much he meant to me?
你知道他对我意味着什么吗？
We were friends.
我们是朋友
Both focused
on the northern reserve issue.
我们俩一直在集中精力解决北部保护区的事
It kinda seems you have a theory,
don't you?
我不知道 但我觉得你有想法 对吧?
I do.
有
Would you like to share?
愿意说说吗?
I have a theory
我觉得
that whatever happened to him
is gonna happen to me.
会发生在我身上的 就是他经历的那种事 对吧?
He disappeared, didn't he?
他失踪了 对吧?
The last time I saw Leonardo,
he was good.
我最后一次见莱昂纳多时 他状态很好
Very good.
非常好
And I think it's possible
he might be even better now.
我觉得他现在可能更好了
What matters is that you know
you can get your life together here.
关键是你得知道 你能在这把日子理顺
All you gotta do is hurry
figure out what you wanna do.
你只要快点做决定
Take a stand.
表个态
We got nothing else to talk about.
我们就没什么可谈的了
Make a decision.
做个决定
Decide whatever you want,
but do it.
想怎么决定都行 但你得决定
And I...
而我
can help you.
可以帮你一把
50,000 euros.
5万欧元
Whenever you want.
你想什么时候拿都行
Wherever you want.
你想在哪拿都行
No receipts, no...
不留收据
Quick and simple.
又快又简单
100?
10万?
Listen.
听着
I'm not gonna waste my time explaining
我不想浪费时间解释
why things gotta be
the way they gotta be
为什么事情必须按那样来
and who is involved.
也不想说牵扯到谁
I'm not asking you to do this or that.
我不是要你做这做那
I'm asking you to take a stand.
我只要你表态
Could you tell me where we're going?
我们要去哪 你能告诉我吗?
Don't you trust me?
你不相信我？
Could you stop being so curious?
你能别这么好奇吗?
Do you trust me?
你信我吗?
I don't wanna know the answer.
我不想听答案
I saw your friend.
我见过你朋友
Oh yeah?
是吗?
- Who?
- Horácio
-谁？-奥拉西奥
The great Horácio?
大名鼎鼎的奥拉西奥?
The great Horácio.
就是他
How was that experience?
那感觉怎么样?
Have you seen him lately?
你最近见过他吗？
We talked.
我和他聊了一下
About?
聊什么？
Does he have any special interest
in the construction of this road?
他是不是对这条路的建设特别上心?
Not that I know of,
but knowing Horácio, he might.
但按奥拉西奥的性子 很可能有
Why?
怎么了？
Because he offered me a lotta money
因为他提出给我一大笔钱
to finish the report earlier.
要我提前把报告做完
A lotta money,
how much are we talking about?
一大笔钱，是多大笔？
100,000 euros.
10万欧元
100,000 euros?
10万欧元?
-Yes.
10万欧元? -对
I never thought you'd be worth so much.
没想到你这么值钱
100,000 euros?
10万欧元?
He offered me 150,000 euros.
他给我开了15万欧元
Sorry, I'm still thinking
about the 100,000!
抱歉 我还在想那10万欧元
Damn!
天啊
He says construction must begin
before the rainy season.
他说雨季前必须开工
He's in a hurry.
他很急
What did you say?
你怎么说?
I said no, obviously.
当然是拒绝
- Obviously
- It's insulting
-当然-这太侮辱人了
Insulting.…
侮辱
But weren't you almost done
with the report?
但你的报告不是快写完了吗?
-Yes.
And from what I gathered,
-是－而且我听说
firom an ecological point of view
it's beneficial, right?
从生态角度看是有好处的 对吧？
Ecology can be many things.
生态这个概念可以
Like what?
比如呢?
Are you considering the possibility
I might take that money?
你是觉得我可能会收那笔钱吗?
No, Sérgio.
不 塞尔吉奥
I'm trying to figure out
我只是想弄明白
why you've been offered 150,000 euros.
为什么他们要给你15万欧元
I told you.
我已经跟你解释过了
I already have all the data,
but I don't wanna rush it.
而且我手里数据都齐了 但我不想火急火燎的
I wanna do a good job.
我想做得扎实点
But if you already have all the data,
既然你数据都齐了
what's keeping you from finishing
and handing in the report?
是什么让你还没完成并上交报考呢？
I wanna follow the right procedure.
因为我要按正确流程来
And this ain't it.
可这事没那么简单
Forget it, it was insulting.
Never mind.
算了 刚才太冒犯了 当我没说
- Insulting?
- Yeah, it disgusts me.
-冒犯？-是的，它让我恶心
It's disgusting.
太恶心了
Disgusting?
恶心?
You know what's disgusting, Sérgio?
恶心？你知道什么才叫恶心吗 塞尔吉奥?
The power some people have
to say no to 150,000 euros.
是有些人居然能对15万欧元说不
The importance some people
can give to money,
是有些人能把钱看得那么轻
that's what's disgusting.
这才是恶心
It's dirty money.
那是脏钱
What about the money you earn?
那你赚的钱呢?
Is your salary clean?
你工资就干净吗?
You know what's disgusting?
你知道什么才叫恶心吗？
People being cursed
because of where they were born
有人因为出生地就被诅咒
and not having their basic needs met.
连基本需求都满足不了
It's people like you coming here
and saying no to 150,000 euros.
是像你这样的人来到这儿 还能拒绝15万欧元
Don't you realize that dirty money
你不明白那是脏钱
comes from exploiting
these people you're talking about?
那钱来自对那些人的剥削
And don't you realize
your salary is dirty?
那难道你就不明白 你的工资也是脏的吗?
That your job is dirty?
你的工作也很脏吗?
You think the money coming from
the World Bank and Europe is clean?
你觉得从世界银行和欧洲来的钱就干净吗？
That's called relieving your conscience,
这叫赎罪感
something rich people use
to help the poor, those with nothing,
富人用来施舍穷人 那些一无所有的人
those who need to be helped,
那些需要被帮的人
incapable of governing themselves.
那些连自己都管不好的人
And I'm glad we're incapable of that.
我反而庆幸我们做不到那点
I'm glad we rely on an outsider
我感到庆幸我们依赖外来者
to finish a report on a road
来替我们把一条路的报告做完
and offer him 150,000 euros
然后我们还能给他15万欧元
so he can have the purity to say no.
让他有说不的纯洁性
So you'd take the money, is that it?
那你会收钱 是这个意思吗?
Is that it?
是这样吗?
I don't have the power
to say no to 150,000 euros.
我没那个底气对15万欧元说不
Yet.
现在还没有
Tell me something then.
那你告诉我
Imagine you got that money.
What would you do with it?
假如你拿到那笔钱 你会怎么用?
I think you must ask yourself that.
我觉得你该问问你自己
If you wanna go to the Maldives...
要是你想去马尔代夫…
Oh, wait!
哦 等等！
You'll buy a house for your mom.
你会给你妈买房
No!
You'll pay for your nephews' college.
不 你会供你的侄子们上大学
You'll give it to an orphanage here.
你还会给这儿的孤儿院捐上一笔
Because you'll want to help,
after everything that's given to you.
因为别人帮过你 你也想帮人
Ain't that how this works?
不就是这样运作的吗？
And you'll leave feeling good,
because you helped humanity.
然后你心满意足地走人 觉得自己帮了人类
Turn right at the end of this road.
到这条路的尽头 右转
- Can I park here?
-Yeah.
-能把车停这儿吗？-可以
Why the long face?
拉着脸干嘛?
Finally!
总算到了
Drop that face, I'm here.
You know what traffic's like.
别摆脸色 你也知道这路有多堵
Lemme introduce you
to my friend, Sérgio.
我给你介绍我朋友 塞尔吉奥
My mom, Domingas
- How're you doing?
-我妈多明加斯-你好吗?
I'm good.
我挺好
Sérgio looks weak...
塞尔吉奥看着挺虚的啊…
Mom, he knows Creole.
妈 他听得懂克里奥尔语
I made some food, cachupa...
我做了吃的, 卡舒帕
Good afternoon, family!
下午好，家人们！
Come sit down.
来坐
Don't get up, Aunt.
姨 别站起来啦
How are you?
- I'm okay.
-你怎么样？-我挺好
How are you?
你怎么样？
You look beautiful!
你真漂亮
Come sit here, Seroio.
- How are you, Uncle?
-塞尔吉奥 来坐这-叔叔 你好吗?
Look, that's Sérgio.
看 这就是塞尔吉奥
Your special someone?
- No, he's my friend.
-是你的对象吗？-不是，他只我朋友
He's not my someone.
他不是我对象
Where's he gonna sit, Mom?
妈 他坐哪?
Where can I wash my hands?
我去哪能洗手?
In the bathroom.
去卫生间
Show him where to wash his hands.
带他去洗把手
Can you gimme some...
能给我点…
There's a sick person in here.
这屋里有个病人
He's been sick for a long time...
他病很久了
He can't eat anything.
什么都吃不下
Throws up everything he eats.
吃什么吐什么
We must pray for his recovery.
我们得为他祈祷康复
Come.
来吧
Bathroom's in there.
卫生间在里面
Thank you
- You're welcome.
-谢谢 -不客气
I'm on a diet, but I haven't lost much.
我在减肥，但还没瘦多少呢
He's coming to visit.
他要来探望
Who's coming to visit?
谁要来探望?
I'm gonna get a chair.
我去拿把椅子
Don't get up,
别起身
sit down.
坐着
Are you going to Lisbon?
你要去里斯本吗?
Are you?
你呢?
Are you going to Lisbon?
你要去里斯本吗?
I want to go too.
Will you take me?
我也想去 你会带我去吗？
No, we're not gonna take you.
不 我们不带你去
Do you know Pecixe?
你知道佩希谢吗?
No.
不知道
Do you know Biombo?
你知道比翁博吗?
Biombo?
比翁博?
Uncle!
叔叔
He's a guest! Sérgio's a guest!
他是客人 塞尔吉奥是客人
So tell him, he'll understand.
那就跟他说一下，他就懂了
Pecixe is the island
of the Manjak people.
佩希谢是曼雅克人的岛
In the north?
在北边吗?
Yeah, up north.
对在北边
Is it far from here?
离这远吗?
No...
不远
It's not far, but it's an island.
不算远 但它是个岛
He'll go with you.
他会跟你去
Yes! Let's go to Pecixe together.
好 我们一起去佩希谢
I'm gonna fall asleep here.
我就在这睡会
Don't worry, we'll wake you.
别担心我们会叫醒你
Who wants beer?
谁要啤酒?
One.
一瓶
Beer. Two.
啤酒两瓶
All ofus
- All of you?
-我们都要-你们全都要吗?
Okay.
行
Everyone.
每个人都要
Let's see if we have enough.
我看看够不够
One for each.
一人一瓶
Just a minute.
等一下
Sérgio.
塞尔吉奥
Sorry.
抱歉
Juice?
果汁?
Are you worried about your diet
-I can have lunch now.
你还担心身材吗？-我现在能吃午饭了
Here's to all of you!
敬你们大家
Sérgio, thank you so much!
Thank you for what?
For his visit!
谢谢他的来访
Diára's here!
Do I look good?
我戴着好看吗?
Only if you wear a diadem.
We're almost a family.
我们差不多是一家子了
We're almosta
- A family? Where?
-我们差不多是一家子了-一家子？在哪?
Diára.
迪娅拉
Wake up.
醒醒
We're here.
到了
我们到了
Can you still climb stairs?
你还能爬楼梯吗?
Your hair!
你的头发
Sérgio!
塞尔吉奥
I think I'm gonna go.
我想我得走了
You're gonna go? Why?
你要走吗为什么?
I'm tired.
我累了
Come in.
来吧
No
Please.
-不要-求你了
I'm tired, I'm sleepy.
我累了也困了
Didn't you wanna meet my family?
你不是想见见我家吗
Didn't you say you wanted
to know everything about me?
你不是说想把我都了解透吗?
Well?
所以?
It's done.
心愿完成了
Family lunch.
What are you doing tomorrow?
你明天干嘛?
Nothing
没事
I'm gonna hang out with Jota.
我去和若塔混
Maybe he'll stay over.
他可能会住一晚
And you could come with us.
你也可以一起来
Do you wanna come?
Yeah.
想
Yeah?
- Cool.
And I would really like it
我也很想
if you sat down and watched.
你能坐着看
Huh?
啊？
I would really like it
我也很想
if you sat down and watched.
你能坐下来看
Wait a minute.
等一下
You're joking, right?
你在开玩笑吧?
No
- Yes, you are.
- 不-你就是
I'm not.
我没有
You enjoy making fun of me?
No.
-你就爱拿我开玩笑-不
Sometimes, but I'm not joking now.
有时候会但这次我没开玩笑
Are you serious?
-Yes.
-你说真的？-真的
Are you playing hard to get
my Marcelina?
你这是欲擒故纵吗我的玛塞丽娜?
Shouldn't you be in the woods?
你不是应该在林子里吗?
Don't tell anyone you saw me
and Ill pretend I didn't see you either.
Hello.
Renato. Pleasure
- Hello. Sérgio
-雷纳托幸会-你好塞尔吉奥
Allgood?
- All good.
-都好吧？-都好
What a beautiful day!
With this sun, what else do you need?
这天真好这太阳真舒服还要什么?
The famous guilty pleasure.
所谓的罪恶快感
Guilty pleasure?
罪恶快感?
I want to be the tooth
我想当牙齿
And the knife
也想当把刀
I want to be the knife
想当那把刀
And the cut
也想当伤口
In one single red kiss
只用一个鲜红的吻
I was born in the sea breeze
我生在海风里
My only rest
我唯一的安歇
Is the storm
是风暴
My bed is a hurricane
我的床是飓风
I am the anger
我是怒火
And the cure
也是解药
The search for sin and counsel
追寻罪恶与劝诫
The space between pain
在疼痛
And comfort
和安慰之间
The struggle between the light
在光和镜子之间
And the mirror
拉扯
Good afternoon!
- Hello, good afternoon.
下午好-下午好
Could you give us a ride? This way.
能捎我们一程吗这条路下去
A ride.
捎一程
Okay.
行
Straight ahead?
-继续走-直走吗?
Keer
- Straight ahead?
-直走吗？-继续开直走?
- Straight ahead.
是的-直走
We're good here.
我们到这下就行
Here?
这里?
IIl stop here.
那我就停这
Thank you.
谢谢
谢谢你啊
We're meeting over there.
Okay, okay.
-我们在那边碰头-行行
They said Atuma died.
他们说阿图马死了
Really?
- Really.
-真的？-真的
How sad.
真难受
He was buried yesterday.
他昨天就下葬了
What happened?
They said he was sick
had a stomachache.
他们说他病了肚子疼
Necado took him to the hospita
and he died there.
加多带他去医院他就死在那了
- He's putting his hand in the water.
-他怎么说的？-他把伸进了
Don't do that.
别这样
You'll drown us.
你会把我们都淹死的
- Don't put your hand in the water.
-这好吗？-别把伸进水里
- You'd better not.
-不行吗？-你最好别
Crocodiles?
有鳄鱼?
There are crocodiles inside.
里面有鳄鱼
In the water.
就在水里
Can I help?
要帮忙吗?
- Yes. Can I?
-划桨？-是的我来?
Come and sit here.
过来坐这儿
- He's tired.
-别坐好坐好-他累了
- Yeah, that's it.
-让他坐着吧-对就是这样
Let's see how he does it.
看他能不能行
paddle?
- Can I?
你想划吗？-我来?
Paddle.
划吧
That's it. You're paddling.
对就你来划
Paddl
- Go on.
-划吧-继续
Paddle.
划
That's it.
对
Paddle hard.
用力划
Come on.
加油
He's tired.
他累了
The piragua's moving.
独木舟动起来了
You see those people over there?
你看到那边那些人了吗?
What's the name of this tabanca?
这个村子叫什么？
This one? Djobel.
这儿吗？乔贝尔
Where
Do you know?
委员会代表在哪？你知道吗?
- He isn't?
－他不在-他不在吗?
No, but his wife's here.
What's his name?
His wife?
他老婆?
-The man.
-还是那个男的？-那个男的
Baciro.
巴西罗
And the wife?
那他老婆呢?
The wife? Isabel
他老婆？依莎贝尔
lsabel.
依莎贝尔
they do in Djobel?
你们讲的语是和乔贝尔那一样的吗?
but we don't know theirs.
他们能听懂我们说的但我们听不懂他们的
Their language is complex.
他们的语很复杂
Are there rice paddies around here?
这附近有稻田吗?
There. Can you see them?
在那你看见了吗?
You see them?
你看见没?
Hello!
你好
How are you?
你好吗?
Yes.
-都还好吗？-还行
Is Mr. Baciro here?
巴西罗先在吗?
No, he's at the school.
不在他在学校
At the school.
在学校…
Can I go over there?
我能过去吗?
Hold on, I"Ill call him.
等等我打给他
lsabel.
依莎贝尔
Can I go see the cistern?
我能去看看蓄水池吗？
Sure, you can go.
行你去吧
lsabel!
依莎贝尔
How do you get to the other houses?
你们怎么去别的房子?
How do you do it?
你们怎么过去?
You paddle.
划过去
At low tide you can walk.
退潮就能走
At high tide, you take the canoe.
涨潮的话就坐独木舟
Is that how it was in the old days?
以前也是这样吗?
In the old days..
以前…
was there this much water?
以前水也这么多?
No.
没有?
Was it less?
更少吗?
Less?
更少?
What do you do
你们怎么弄到
to get freshwater to drink?
能喝的淡水?
-I take the canoe.
－你们怎么弄？-坐独木舟
- We take the canoe to Djifunco.
-独木舟？-我们坐独木舟去迪丰科
Is it far?
远吗?
That way.. past Elalab.
那边过了埃拉拉布
Past..
要过…
40 minutes?
40分钟?
More?
还要更久?
- Bernardete's waiting.
-是这吗？-贝尔纳黛特在等着
-Yes.
－她在等？-对
-穿裙子那个？-对
Hey, woman!
喂你女人
Your woman called you several times!
Good morning!
早上好
Eyerythinea
- Yes!
一切都好吗？-对
and were asking 10,000 xof per bag.
她说昨天你拿了牡蛎并且每袋要价1万
She's sitting there waiting for you.
她坐那儿等你呢
- 8,000 xof.
-我应该卖多少钱？-8千
is having her ass kicked today.
她说今天特蕾莎被狠狠地教训了
What did I do?
我干了什么?
You raised the price.
你把价抬高了
that's the price I gave her.
不是特蕾莎提高了价格是我给她定的价格
and ruined the business.
他们说她今年来把意都给搅了
s the thl
they buy it for 8,000 xof.
这是他们第三次以8千的价格购买
And we're not gonna lower it.
现在我们提高了价格并且不会降
They'll see.
让他们试试
they can buy it.
如果他们想要以1万购买他们可以买
That's it.
就这样
for 8,000 xof.
她说她从来没有以8千购买过牡蛎
10,000, not 8,000.
1万不是8千
Yeah, 10,000
对1万
She's waiting for her.
她在等她
to sell the oysters for 8,000.
奥迪莉亚她说她在等你以8千卖牡蛎
Okay.
行
to sell them for 8,000
他们说她在等你以8千西法郎卖它们
This is her house.
这就是她家
You can go in.
你进去吧
Where did you write it?
你写到哪了?
-Yes?
-奥尔加？-嗯?
Why did you write it like this?
你怎么写成这样?
Kumä?
库马奇?
We're okay.
我们挺好
Hello, kids.
嗨孩子们
How are you?
你们好吗?
Answer it
– We are well.
-回话-我们挺好
Are you?
你呢?
We are well.
我们都挺好
Olga, sught you some things
Some things?
-奥尔加我给你带了点东西-带了东西?
For my children
-Yes.
-给我孩子的？-对
Things...
东西…
What's your name?
你叫什么?
You're not throwing that away.
别把那个扔了
What's your name?
你叫什么?
Sérgio.
塞尔吉奥
I'm friends with Bojan.
我和布贾那是朋友
I've heard abol VOU
on the phone.
我在电话里听他说起过你
How are you?
你好吗?
I'm okay.
我挺好
How's your family?
- Everyone's fine.
-你家都好吗？-都好
I brought some things for your family.
我给家里带了点东西
It's a big bag
I thought it had more.
一大袋我还以为有更多呢
This ain't much
It's good, but it ain't much.
不多也算好但真是不多
Bojan said
he was gonna send a lotta stuff.
布贾那说会送很多
But where's the seven-gallo
diesel jerrycan?
可那7加仑柴油油桶呢?
Does Bojan usually bring
布贾那平时会带
a seven-gallon diesel jerrycan?
Yes. Where is it?
对啊在哪?
didn
- Why?
-没带-为什么?
I"II bring it next time.
下次我带过来
No, that's not what we agreed.
不这不是我们说好的
On the phone,
电话里头
he said he was gonna bring more stuff
This ain't enough.
他说会带更多来的这不够
That's not what he said.
他不是这么说的
This ain't good.
这样不行
I'm gonna call him.
我给他打电话
Olga, I wanna talk to you
about something.
About the water pump
那个水泵
that broke.
坏掉了
Why did it break?
it's on the land of the ira
他们不想要这泵在伊拉的土地上
The ira doesn't want the water pump?
伊拉不想要水泵?
The ira doesn't want the pump.
伊拉不想要
What about the people?
那其他人呢?
They don't want it either.
他们也不想要
What about a road
crossing the bolanha?
那条穿过稻田的路呢?
By the rice paddies.
从稻田那边过
You want the road?
你想要那条路
For cars and motorcycles.
给汽车和摩托走?
I don't care
whether there's a road or not.
有没有路我都不在乎
Money's good for other things,
钱该用在别处
not to go around buying food
when we can work.
而不是用来买吃的我们能干活
We produce onions, tomatoes.
我们种洋葱番茄…
Veqrow av
so we have everything
我们有菜园子什么都有
Do you have bananas?
你们有香蕉吗?
Bananas, mangoes..
香蕉芒果…
Everything.
什么都有
Oranges, grapefruits, tangerines..
橙子葡萄柚橘子…
We have everything here.
这里什么都有
you gotta buy everything
可在城什么都得花钱买
if we have a road or not.
有没有路我都不在乎
Here, we can get oysters, fish.
这儿能捡生蚝还能抓鱼…
Fresh fish! Straight outta the sea.
我们不放冰块新鲜的鱼直接从海里捞
with pilau rice
我们煮一煮配抓饭吃
But in the city you gotta buy everything
Even firewood.
可在城什么都得买甚是柴
I cut this firewood in the woods
but in the city you have to buy it.
柴火我可以在林子里砍城里得花钱买
ater to drink there
But not here.
在城连喝都得花钱但这儿不用
Electricity... You people pay rent.
还有电费你们还要交房租
don't pay
this place is mine.
我不用交房租这地方是我的
the end o
if I don't die,
我死的那天我也在自己屋里
I"Il be in my house.
我就在我家
don'towea
My life is my own.
我不欠谁的我的命归我自己
Sérgio.
塞尔吉奥
I set a bed here,
that's where you'll sleep.
我给你铺了床你就睡这
There's some rice.
这有点米
This is what we harvested this year.
这是我们今年收的
This one too.
这堆也是
It's good.
多好啊
It's this year's rice.
这是今年的新米
This is last year's.
这些是去年的
From here all the way down there.
这是去年的从这里一直到那边都是
It was all the way up here.
I ate this much.
一直延伸到这我吃了这么多
This is what's left.
现在就剩这些
Here?
- This is where you'll sleep.
-这儿吗？-你就睡这儿
I've made the bed
床我都铺好了
You can lie down.
-Thank you.
-你躺着吧-谢谢
You can lie down.
你躺下吧
Can I lie down?
- Yes, you can.
-能躺下吗？-能
You can lie down.
你躺吧
Thank you.
谢谢
I'm glad you came to visit.
你能来看我我很高兴
Rui, what if there was a road here?
In this area, close to your...
就在这片区域离…
your place, your house?
你家你住的地方很近
our parents had a lot of bolanhas
是以前我们父辈有很多稻田
But now, with all this climate change,
可现在气候变化成这样
the volume of salt water has risen
海水上来了
takene muehof the bolanha
in the tabanca.
把大部分稻田和村子都淹了
destroyed everything.
- Of course
ebolanhas we have now
are very small
compared to what our parents had.
很我们父母辈那时比的话
ne
to go study in the city.
年轻人离开村子去读书
People don't wanna stay here.
Only old people stay
but they're not strong enough to work.
留下的都是没干那活
That's also why production fell.
产量也就跟着下来了
So, if a road went through here
那如果这里有条路
here was
a more direct connection to..
能直接连上
to your tabanca,
you think people would stay?
Of course.
当然会
hatevervthing
in Guinea-Bissau is in Bissau.
现在几内亚比绍的都在比绍
If you want a job, you go to Bissau,
想找工作就得去比绍
if you want to study, you go to Bissau.
Butifthe State
that reached the whole country
可要是有项目能覆盖全国
and supported initiatives
that allowed young people
to work in their villages,
I don't think they'd leave.
我觉得他们就不会跑
tdon'tvou think a road
would disturb or even destroy
可你不觉得修路会打扰甚至毁掉
some ofthe oul
its traditions?
村子的化和传统吗?
You think they could resist?
你觉得他们能抵住吗?
Roads are part of a country's
or a village's development.
路是国家和村子发展的一个部分
And we struggle a lot
我们现在最大的麻烦是路太难走
because cars can't get here.
因为车进不来
or a pregnant woman is giving birth,
要是有人生病或者女人要生孩子
how will they make it to the hospital?
也不知道怎么去医院
There's no transportation.
这里没有交通
sa-roag
it would be better for the village.
我觉得有路对村子会更好
would just hop on a car and go.
谁想去城里办事上车就能走
How many people live here?
这里住多少人?
Elalab?
- In Elalab, more or less.
在埃拉拉布吗？-在埃拉拉布差不多
It varies..
大概是
In dry weather, around 400.
旱季400人
Durina the seaso
they can be up to 600.
雨季能到600
There's more people
during the rainy season?
Young peoplev
- Come back?
-那些年轻人…－会回来吗?
Those who went to study in the city.
去城里读书的那些人
Who came up with this?
这是谁想出来的?
Who invented this system?
这套系统是谁发明的?
lt'e been going on for cen
since our grandparents' time.
从我们祖父母那会儿就一直这样
The pipes weren't the same, though.
只是那时用的管子不一样
They'd cut the trunks off palm trees.
他们会把棕榈树干劈开
Yes
以前都是这样？-对
Kassumai!
你们好啊
pw are
- We're okay.
-你们好吗？-我们挺好
You're okay?
-Yes
-你们都好吗？-好
- Kassumai kep!
-你好-你好
Everything okay?
都还好吗?
I'm looking for the water pump.
我在找一个水泵
Behind eusa'shouse
near the school.
在学校附近那栋房子旁边
We know where it is. Over there.
我们知道在那边
There?
那边?
Yes
-能带我去吗？-可以
Now?
现在去?
Let's go.
走吧
Thank you.
谢谢
Luis, come here!
路易斯过来
Come back here!
给我回来
He's not coming?
No.
不
Hold on.
等等
and leave old people behind.
你们把年轻人带走把老人丢下
Can't he come?
他不能来吗?
No.
不行
Why?
为什么?
No reason.
没有为什么
Can't he come and show..
eadolts
and only the children remain.
都被你带走了就只剩孩子了
The road... we don't want it.
那条路 我们不要
I don't understand.
我不懂
I don't understand you.
我听不懂你
You don't?
你不懂?
He's not coming with you.
他不会跟你去
No?
不去?
- Why not?
－不-为什么不能去?
Youive taken all the young men
and left the old people behind.
你们把这里的都带了就只剩孩子了
Do your parents work here?
你们母在这活吗?
Yes.
对
Really? Everyone's?
Yes
-真的？你们父母都是？-对
Who's playing now?
现在是谁在踢?
Brazil.
巴西
Brazil and Spain.
巴西对西班牙
Like this?
像这样?
Yes.
对
Was it too much?
剃太多了吗?
You're bald now.
你现在都秃了
Yes, yes.
就是就是
It'll grow right back.
看上去很酷很快就会长回来的
What do you think, Elvis?
你觉得呢埃尔维斯?
Sorry.
抱歉
What would cars bring?
车会给这里带来什么？
What do you think cars would bring?
你们觉得车会给这里带来什么?
What would cars bring?
车到底会带来什么？
Would it change anything?
Hello?
在吗?
Sérgio?
塞尔吉奥?
Hello?
在吗?
Sérgio?
塞尔吉奥?
Have some water.
来喝点水
Here. Sérgio?
来塞尔吉奥?
Open your mouth.
张嘴
Here, here.
来来
Open it.
张开
Have some water.
喝点水
Are you okay?
你没事吧?
Open your mouth
It"ll do you good.
张嘴对你有好处
Swallow it.
咽下去
Better?
好点了吗?
I only saw your text this morning
我今天早上才看到你的短信
I'm sorry I took so long.
对不起让你等久了
Have some more.
再喝点
Easy, that's it.
行就这样
Open it.
睁大
I enjoyed doing this.
我挺乐意帮你点这个
Thank you.
How did you get in here?
你怎么进来的?
Huh?
啊？
It's good.
挺好
It's really weird, but really good.
味道很怪但真挺好吃的
Good morning.
早上好
Can I leave this with you?
我能把这个放你这儿吗?
Ofcourse.
当然可以
Someone will come
looking for a yellow folder.
会有人来找一个黄色件夹
Okay.
好
Thank you
- You're welcome.
Is this boat going to the islands?
你好打扰一下这船是去岛上的吗?
这船是去岛上的吗?
Yes
对对
Hey, buddy!
喂朋友
Buddy, gimme a hand!
朋友帮忙搭把手
Anotacāo KATE SARAGACO-GOMES
IMA I ATTANTIN
Direcao de Som JULES VALEUR
Desenho de Som PABLO LAMAR
Colorista CLAUDIU DOAGA
Direcao de Producao EDUARDO NASSER
GLÓRIA MELLANO
Producao CRISTIANA FORTE
Segunda Assistente de Imagem JULIANE RUPAR
Chefe Electricista VERNAL SANTOS
EDUARDO CARVALHO
AHN IA ANCDICANI
Cabeleireira AMICAMARA
Efeitos Visuais MARTAO VAGNER
Segundo Assistente de Realizacao DIOGO ALLEN
Apoio a Realizacāo DIOP MAMADOU
Duplo Sérgio PAUL TERGEIST
DINTA DNCANNDE
Professor de Criolo MARINHO DE PINA
Contabilista HELENA RODIGUES
EQUIPA DE POS-PRODUCAO
Assistente de Edicao de Som EVER GALEANO
Engenheiro de Foley RAUL JOOKEN
Artista de Folev FELIX BARREIRA
Consultora Musical DANIELA SOARES
Estúdio de Pós-Producao AVANPOST MEDIA
Oraanizacao de Ficheiros BOGDAN GEAMBASU
Créditos ANDREI ARMASELU
Preparacao das Imagens AMANDINE MOULINET
JINANA CARRAI
DISTRIBUICAO PORTUGAL
Comunicacao FRANCISCA RAMIREZ
Camera e Luz PANAVISION
Broker SIACI SAINT HONORE
Contabilidade PLENO DE RAZAO
Drnduran CFI FSTF AIVFS
Supervisao de Pós-Producao MARTA LEMOS
Distribuicāo TERRATREME FILMES
Auditor KARMEN & ASSOCIES
Produtores IOANA LASCAR
Auditor MADIA JAMII
Drivare
ERNANDOJUNIO
Aconselhamento Legal GABRIELA ROCHA - SENNA ADVOGADOS
Distribuidor Brasileiro VITRINE FILMES
DIOGO TEIXEIRA, DJADJAS (SAMBA CAMARA], EATOR CASSAMA, EDMERSON FERNANDO NHOQUE, EDMILSON AZEVEDO,
EDY EDMERSON NHOOUE. FATINHA PEREIRA. FATINHA PEREIRA. FERNANDO NOHOUE. GABRIEL NANGO. GLEIGUEM LEMVABOH
WANG BIGQUAN, YANG GUOHUA, YANUSSO INDJAI, YAYA.
ABDULAI SISSE, ABDURAMANE JALO, ABI SANE, ABI SANELIBANIO PORANCA, ABUDO COROBO, ADAO,
ADEL DJEME. ADJETOU MAMI. AECIO VAZ. AESSATU SARLETE RODRIGUES. AFONSO DA COSTA.
AHMEDOU M'BARECK, AIBIL GOMES, AIDA SEIDI, ALADJE SENE SISSE, ALBADI DJATA,
AUGUSTO NOTA CORREIA. AZIZ MEDSALM. BABA. BABA MANE. BABE SMRDIMTT. BARTOLOMEU DIAS. BARTOLOMEU M. MILACO.
TI DOMINGOS BIAGUE, BIDAMATCHA TCHAMI, BONI, BONIFACIO TE, BOTCHE BALDE, BRAIMA (
DEISE REIS. DELFIM PEREIRA. DEMBA BALA. DEUSA INTUMBO. DEVLYN. DIANA INDI. DICO FRANCISCO GOMES DJU. DILMA COIMBRA.
DINGONA SAMBA, DIOGO MONTEIRO, DJADJA, DJADJAS (SAMBA CAMARA), DJAMILA NHAGA, DJESSI, DJEY SARB, DOMINGOS MENDES
IRO, DOUTOR PAULINO FANDA, DZENABE BALDE, EDNELCIA SANCA, EL MAMY, ELDOMAR DA SILVA, E
FATU SAMANANGO. FATUMATA SEIDE. FELICIANO BUTELHO. FELICIANO PINTO BIAGUE. FELISBERTO AUGUSTO DA SILVA. FELIZADARE.
ISNABA NHAU NANGANA, ISSAC BADJAN, ITCHO JE, IUNESSA DJALO, VA GOMES, VAILTON JOSE, VALUCIA, VAMIRA TOBA, IVAN DA MATA,
AIA GALISSA KOUYATE, LANDIM TCHANTCHELAM, LANICA SA, LASSANA SANO, LEODICIANA MONTEIRO, LEOPOLDO DUANHI
LEOPOLDO SANA, LIBANIO PORANCA, LILIANA SEMEDO, LINHO LOPES (ESPECIAL), LINO GOMES, LINO LOPES, LIVIA LATTANZIO,
LOCADIA DOS SANTOS, LOTE BISSUMA, LUANA PEREIRA, LUCIA VERZOTTI, LUCINDA COAUSENDE BLEIQUE, LUDI GAMA, LUDMILA DJU,
NIA SILVA, MARCELINO ALFREDO, MARCELO LOPES, MARCOS LOPES DA SILVA, MARIAMA CAMARA, MARIAMA MAI
MICHAEL DJATA, MIGALDINU, MIGUEL BLEIQUE, MILDO NANQUE, MILOCO INCANHA, MILTON TEIXEIRA, MINDANA N'FANDA, MIQUELA GOMES
PEDRO BARROS, PEDRO CA, PESADAO, PUTARA TE, QUINTA, RACHIDE SA, RAMATULAI CANDE, RAQUEL CORREIA, RASTA BALANTA,
ROSA MENDES, ROTCINHA, RUBEN JESUS, RUCAS GRAIMA, RUDGULIT QUEBE, RUI INTCHULA, RUI LALES DJATA
TILBRA BIANGA, TITO BADJAN, TONY JUNIOR, TOTALA DJATA, TU, TULIMA SANCA, TUTI, UDE BAIO, UMABRO BALDE, UMARO BAIO, URI SILA,
USSAI DJAU. USSUMANE BUARO. USSUMANI GALISSA. VALDINHO ARLETE. VANESIO DJATAN. VENANCIO VAZ. VIDAL. VIRIATO MELACO.
INTERPRETACAO: ORQUESTRA SUPER MAMA DJOMBO INTERPRETACAO: ORQUESTRA SUPER MAMA DJOMBO
JHONNV IFANNRN SANNOVAI CARNONA AKA. SAINT CARNONA
ASTER: MC PREGO PREGO
AMA PUBLISHING/UNIVERSAL MUSIC PUBLISHING, S.L.C
FMILIA Z ISACFM. ANISSA ISACFM
PUBLISHINGPRODUC
CASO IDENTIFIQUE NA BANDA SONORA DESTE FILME CONTEUDO DA SUA AUTORIA, E NAO TENHA SIDO CONTACTADO PARA ESTE EFEITO,
utro à Zahra Horma e ao Mohamed Lemine Ahmed, que nos abriram a porta de tanta coisa
Daniela Soares, Patricia Faria, Filipa Falcāo e Joana Bravo.
pessoas na TERRATREME que ajudaram a tornar este filme possivel. A toda a equipa, actores e figurantes
Ana Gomes, Ana e Maimouna, Ana Ramos, Andreia Martinho - Cinemate, Anicete, Aninha Barros,
Mama Saliu, Maira e Joaquim Letras, Mafalda Fresco, Magalie Armand, Mama Saliu,
Michel Plazanet, Miriam Vieira, Mohamed Ahmed, Monsieur Yassine Dalal,
Paula Pripas, Raquel Fernandes, Raquel Laranjo,
Camara Municipal de Bissau, Capitania do Porto de Bissau, Casa do Comum do Bairro Alto,
Uirá Afonso dos Santos, Equipe Kromaki Filmes, Equipe Ancine e BRDE, Air Time Transportadora,
A todos os habitantes da Aldeia de Arame, Budjin e Elalabe
STILL MOVING. DEFILM. BUBBLES PROJECT
INSTITUTO DO CINEMA E DO AUDIOVISUAL
ANCINE - AGENCIA NACIONAL DO CINEMA
BANCO REGIONAL DE DESENVOLVIMENTO DO EXTREMO SUL
RADIO TELEVISAO PORTUGUESA
FUNDO DE APOIO AO TURISMO E AO CINEMA
CREATIVE EUROPE MEDIA OF THE EUROPEAN UNION
AVAND∩CT MCNIA
FILM VIT R
IKROMAKI
ISAN0000-0005-CAF6-0000-B-0000-0000-4